To conclude the class I want to focus on
the future.
I've spent a great deal of time giving you
the history and roots of gamification as
well as the current state of the art and
best practices.
So where's it all going?
What's gamification's going to be like in
two or five or ten or twenty years?
What does the future hold?
I don't know.
No one knows for certainty.
Gamification is still a fairly young field
that's changing very fast even month by
month.
So it would be foolish of me to say I know
exactly what the landscape is going to
look like in the future.
But it's still worth thinking about where
things are going.
And the best way I can conceive of to do
that is to ask you to imagine what would
happen if gamification continued to grow
and expand and become more important to
the point it truly became pervasive in
society.
What would that mean.
What would it be like, and what would it
say about the practice of gamification
that might teach us lessons for today.
Well, the best way I can think of to get
you thinking about those questions is to
show you a short film called Sight that
was made by two Israeli filmmakers, Eran
May-raz and Daniel Lazo.
They actually did it as their graduation
project from a leading Israeli film
school.
And this video, which several people have
already pointed out on the forums and have
had some discussions about is the best
example that I've seen so far to press you
to think about What gamification could
mean if it truly became universal?
And so I'm going to, with the permission
of the filmmakers, have you watch the
video now.
If you've already seen it you can feel
free to skip through it in this video
lecture section.
But, keep in mind.
The film will be the basis of several of
the questions on your final exam.
So you might want to look at it before
during taking that as well.
So without further ado, Sight.
Excellent.
.
Perfect.
Good job.
Excellent.
Well done.
Level complete.
, Welcome, .
.
Snail zombies, from your, backyard.
Life is a journey.
And in this journey, we all want to do
more, experience more, feel more, and
live, with no boundaries.
And why shouldn't we?
Sight System presents, SiteSync.
Feel free, to go anywhere.
Okay, got you.
Oh, hi, hi, Daphne how are you?
Sorry.
It's okay.
You look great.
Thank you.
Love your jacket.
Thanks.
Actually it's, it's a sports jacket.
So that's official than it looks.
What do you mean?
Sorry.
What's the difference between a sports
jacket and a normal one?
I guess the sports jacket is for people
who want to look good even when they are
chased by the police.
[laugh] Yeah.
Anyway I hope you're hungry.
Yeah.
This place has the best burgers in town.
Oh, actually I'm a vegetarian.
Oh.
Yeah.
Really cause.
You didn't say it on your profiles though.
Wow, I don't write everything on my
profile, so.
Oh.
You want to go somewhere else?
No, no, no, I'll find something on the
menu.
Well how about a glass of wine for
starters?
Yeah, great.
Are there any other things on your profile
you didn't write about that I should know
or?
Aren't you scared of jogging by yourself
in the city?
Not really.
Besides I'm?
I hit level five and now I'm a master.
Pretty impressive.
I know.
[laugh] what is scarey though, on my last
route, my site crashed.
It was so scarey.
I didn't see anything, I couldn't find my
way home.
The site doesn't crash.
Well it did.
I was totally lost.
I didn't see anything.
That doesn't happen since our last pack.
Do you work there or something?
Really?
Wow!
What do you do there?
Nothing serious, I'm just a simple
engineer.
Gee, I read about your.
Is it true that you guys and implant stuff
and manipulate people sights?
[laugh] That's just bullshit, but anyway I
don't want to talk about work, not when
I'm here with such a pretty lady.
[laugh] You know you really get me.
You know I can tell what you are thinking
right now.
Really.
But.
Well finished our drinks.
[laugh] How about we go to my place for a
night cap.
Well, you were so good at reading my mind,
you should know what I'm going to say.
Here it is.
Make yourself at home.
.
Nice place you've got here.
It's all right I guess.
A toast.
For perfect night.
.
Why are you drinking?
What's that?
A dating app?
No, no, no, no.
It's for programming.
I cannot believe this.
This is just my luck, a freaking game
junkie.
Disgusting.
Wait.
Do not touch me, you freak.
Pathetic.
I said, wait.
.
Well let's try this again.
,, .