Gameification can be a very powerful
technique for collective action.
For motivating and encouraging large
numbers of people to come together, and
work on a common task or a set of tasks.
I already talked about something related
to this when I described stack overflow.
And showed how the Gameification design
for that site encouraged pro-social, and,
in some cases, collaborative behavior,
like people commenting and responding on
each others questions.
But,
What if you have a specific objective?
Stack Overflow is designed to be a forum
for people learning about and getting
better at programming.
What if you have a task that you want to
solve, and you want to employ the energy
and ideas and enthusiasm of a large number
of people towards it?
There are a number of different scenarios
where this might be the case.
Some of them, we've actually already
looked at.
So, let me give you a framework to
understand what I'm talking about.
I'll draw two axis here.
One of them will say is competitive versus
collaborative.
In other words, are people working
together with each other or against each
other in trying to achieve the task.
And the other one would be top down versus
bottom up.
Traditionally, the way people are
motivated and encouraged to do things is
top down.
Someone says, this is what you will do.
The alternative approach is to do it in a
more bottom up way by getting them to be
motivated to do it themselves.
So in this first quadrant here.
Competitive top down, this would be
grants.
So this is where, a company or foundation
or organization says we want to find
someone who's going to do a certain amount
of research to achieve something or get a
certain result.
And so we'll pick a winner and then give
them the money to do it.
The alternative approach.
That's bottom up, was described in one of
the earlier sessions.
That's where we would put the inducement
prizes.
Still competitive.
People or organizations or groups are
competing to win the prize, but now it's
bottom up.
Anyone can submit to the prize and the
organization only pays out to the winner.
Here on the collaborative side is what I'm
going to talk about more in this lecture.
The traditional approach is to use
employees.
So if you want a group of people to work
together to solve a problem you tell them
to do it.
The alternative though is what's called
crowd sourcing.
Or in some cases, make it work.
This is a family of approaches that
encourage people to come together to
either collaborate with each other or to
each take a small part or a small amount
of effort towards a task.
But the people are not workers for the
entity that puts forth the task, there are
people who are motivated through a bunch
of different mechanisms that I'm about to
talk about, voluntarily to take on the
task.
So.
What is it that might motivate people to
take on a task if it's not for their
employer.
Well, one thing is, of course, money.
So there are a number of platforms,
Amazon's Mechanical Turk which I'm showing
you here is the biggest and best known,
which provide an environment for this
collaborative crowd-sourced micro-work.
For people to voluntarily work on certain
tasks, typically for money, it doesn't
have to be for money but typically, these
are situations where a company wants
something done.
They want someone to go check out a bunch
of websites, or review a bunch of
documents.
Do some sort of tasks that requires some
level of human intelligence.
Amazon,
Calls them here human intelligence tasks,
you may not be able to see it on the
graph, it goes a little small, but they're
tasks that can't easily be done by a
computer because if they could easily be
done by a computer.
We just have a computer do that.
The computers are a lot cheaper and faster
than people, but lots of things require
some degree of thought and discrimination
that humans do well.
So mechanical turk, and other things like
it, are platforms for people to come and
do those tasks, and typically they get
paid a small amount for doing it and this
has been quite successful.
As you see here, there are over 200,000 of
these tasks available today on mechanical
turk.
So, this is one form of crowd sourcing,
but as I talked about throughout the
class, money is not necessarily the only
thing that motivates people.
So is it possible to motivate people to
participate in these crowd source projects
without necessarily paying them to do it?
Indeed it is.
And the way to do it is, to use
Gameification Let me show you a few
examples.
This is something called Fold It.
I didn't put the OL on here but it's just
that fold that.
It Fold it.
This is a site that was developed by some
biomedical researchers at the University
of Washington, and they are working on 3D
protein folding.
It turns out that the three dimensional
shape that a protein molecule folds up
into has a tremendous impact on what it
does in the body.
So if we know the 3-D shape we are much
further along in developing drugs based on
those proteins and those other molecules.
But it's incredibly, computationally
difficult to figure out what shape a
molecule will fold into.
However,
People are really good at figuring this
out, because it's a puzzle.
It's something that involves looking at
the shapes and figuring out the most
efficient configuration.
And so Fold It is a game like system that
gives you some real world proteins and
asks you to figure out the most efficient
layout.
And by making this process game-like.
By making it seem like fun, these
researchers were able to motivate
thousands of people to come together and
work on these problems with some
tremendous success.
So, there was a case in which there was a
molecule that's important for AIDS
research, has to do with a monkey virus
that's similar to AIDS.
Where for fifteen years researchers have
been trying to figure out the 3D fold,
folding shape of that melocule.
And unfolded,
Volunteers were able to figure it out in
just ten days, incredible success and they
had another a number of other examples
like that, where this aspect of making
something feel fun or puzzle-like, and
also telling people that it's part of
helping medical research, it has been very
successful with motivating participation,
which had got in a great results.
Now, the funny thing is a lot of the press
that came out after this development was
announced, involving the monkey virus,
talked about video gamers solving the
problem.
Online gamers were the ones who had solved
the puzzle and, and cracked the, medical
research problem.
And I thought that was kind of ironic
because these people were gamers only in
the sense that Fold It was a game.
It wasn't that Fold It deliberately
recruited only people who actively played
certain kinds of online games.
They were gamers because they were using a
site that was gamified.
Fold It is a very good example but there
are a number of other examples like this
where applying game like structures can
encourage voluntary participation in
crowd-sourced activities.
Here's another one from a company called
Microtask in Finland, where they partnered
with the Finnish National Library, which
was trying to digitize, major, historical
works in Finnish, and they needed people
to, review and proofread, the optical
character recognition.
So, they created this thing called
Digitalkoot, that is basically a game,
where you play these, creatures, I don't
really know what these are.
But, and they're building a bridge across
the river and the component pieces of the
bridge are words that have been
interpreted by the optical character
recognition system.
And you need to see if the words are
correct,
And you use this game to feed in your work
to the process of checking the
digitization of the finished works, and
they were able through this process to,
get a huge number of people to participate
and to review 2.5 million specific
examples in this digitization process.
Again, not by paying people, but by
encouraging them by making it fun.
Now Microtask,
Also has a business that uses the same
game like interfaces in environments where
they do pay people.
The game then just encourages and
increases the level of motivation and then
they go out to paying clients who want to
do thing like form processing who want to
understand optical character recognition
of handwritten forms and you are willing
to pay an amount of money to Microtask
which then could pay a little bit to each
of the participants.
And the company gets back much better
results on the quality of their forms.
The Gameification there becomes not the
only for a motivation but something that
dramatically increases the level of
motivation and gets more people to
participate.
In some cases, crowd sourcing and micro
work can be done without people even fully
understanding that that's what they're
doing.
Luis Von Ahn is a researcher at Carnegie
Mellon University who is one of the
leaders in developing what he calls games
with a purpose.
One of the ones that he originally
developed was this example here called the
ESP game, which is a cute little game that
shows people a picture.
Here we see a bunch of sheep and says,
What is this?
Type in what this is and the same thing is
given to two different people so you type
in here what you think it is and the
system says did you and the other person
type in the same word?
Because if two people looking an image
type in the same word, there's a pretty
high likelihood that, that word
corresponds to the image.
Conversely if people type in different
things, then maybe those are not right and
that provides some more data to the
system.
What's the point of this?
Well it's kinda fun for the players to
figure out if you're matching with other
people, if you get the right description
of something and in fact they got lots of
people to participate.
And then, and try and get a high score,
and engage in it in the same way that I've
talked about for other examples of
Gameification The point of this though for
the company setting this up, is improving
image search.
Very hard for a computer to look at this
and know that this is sheep.
We've got lots of great research on visual
recognition and computer vision, but it's
still not as good as a person doing it.
So, this is a way of improving the quality
of image search and meta-tagging images
for search engines.
And in fact.
Google bought the company, bought the
technology, that von Ahn had developed for
this ESP game in order to improve their
image search.
Now here again, this is not something like
the prior examples, where people are being
told, you're participating in image
search.
People are just being told, here's
something fun, and they're doing it to the
extent that it's fun.
So Gameification can be used both in
situations were people explicitly know
what they're doing or in situations where
they're just being encouraged to
participate in some way in what turns out
to be a crowdsourced activity.
So, what kinds of situations lend
themselves?
Well, well, there need to be tasks that
can be split up easily.
Fairly obvious, it needs to be a task that
lot's of people can work on in parallel.
Either that means each person gets a
little segment of the task or many people
are simultaneously trying to solve the
task.
And needs to be a task, as I've talked
about before.
That people are good at doing because if
either it's to hard for people to do or
it's too easy for computers to do those,
the people are not the best possible
solution.
The second major element is it has to be
something where,
A gamified system is a good motivational
technique.
There are three basic ways people can be
motivated to do something crowd-source.
One is for money.
One is for love.
It's something that they care about,
that's important to them.
The Finnish library example might be a
good example.
That people in that country want to
promote the preservation of Finnish
literature.
Another example was when Jim Gray who was
a famous computer science researcher
disappeared on his boat in the ocean.
People volunteered to scour satellite maps
to try and figure out if they could find
evidence of.
His ship, because they cared a lot about
trying to save this guy who was a very
revered figure in the field.
So they did it not for money, or because
the task was fun, but because they cared
about the result.
So that's another situation and the third
is people being motivated for fun, and,
and this one is really the one that we're
most concerned about in Gameification but
as I talked about with the earlier
examples, more than one of these can be
present and the same time, and fun,
game-like approaches tend to be something
that can magnify the level of engagement.
Even if it's already there and being
re-enforced by some other mechanism.
So.
Inducement prices, virtual economies,
crowd sourcing, are three different
techniques for expanding the scope of
Gameification Going beyond dealing with a
specific objective within a company or for
company visa-vi it's customer base, and as
I've talked about, they can relate to each
other in different ways, but they all rely
upon the same basic motivational
techniques and lessons that we've been
seeing throughout this entire course.