What happens when we add money or things
that work like money to a gamified system?
Then we're in a realm of virtual
economics.
And it's possible to get there in a number
of different ways..
Many gamified systems have rewards,
Things that the players get.
And their often virtual rewards, things
like badges.
Well, if those rewards are persistent, if
their things that endure throughout
participating in the activities,
Especially if the player goes away and
comes back,
Then, they can start to function as
virtual goods. If the system is designed
in a way that gives them some scarcity
value,
Some of them are harder to get than
others, some of them are less widely
available than others, then those virtual
goods can appear to have value to the
players just like a real world physical
good does.
The second way to bring in virtual
economics is to have point systems that
involve points that are tradable or
redeemable i.e.,
You can get the points and use them to buy
a variety of different things in the
gamified system, which themselves are
virtual goods then. Or you can redeem the
points for things in the physical world,
for a coupon or even for money in the
physical world.
In that case we're starting to deal with a
virtual currency.
The points now operate like real money.
They're a currency.
They're a medium of exchange.
What is a dollar or a euro or a renminbi?
It's not a thing in and of itself.
It's just an accounting mechanism that's
tradeable for other real world things that
we want because people in that society
with the backing of governments are
willing to make that exchange. And say, if
you give me a certain amount of money, I
will recognize it and give you some other
kinds of goods.
So, the same thing can be true, of, point
systems in gamified systems.
If they are, exchangeable for other things
that people value, then they can operate
like a currency.
And finally, if the system allows
transactions, if participants in the
virtual system can trade with each other
directly or through some marketplace, then
potentially we're in the realm of a
full-blown virtual economy.
And we've seen this in a variety of
massively multiplayer online games.
Things like EVE Online, as well as some
virtual worlds like Second Life that are
designed to have functioning virtual
economies.
And all these can exist to a greater or
lesser extent in gamified systems.
So, a couple of examples, virtual goods
are a widespread phenomenon in many social
games today.
So games like Farmville.
One of the ways that they were so
successful as businesses, was they
recognized that virtual goods could be
unlocked as a way to monetize the game.
Doesn't cost anything to play, but in
order to achieve certain things easily in
the game, or to get certain rare goods in
the game, you've got to start to spend
real money.
So people think of those virtual goods as
being really worth something, either
because they had to pay for them or
because they had to work very hard to get
them.
This has been so successful that overall
the virtual goods market is estimated at
$7,000,000,000 world-wide in 2010, growing
to $13,000,000,000 by 2016.
But it's not just games.
Gamified systems can have aspects of
virtual goods and virtual currencies and,
potentially, even virtual economies as
well.
Think, in particular, about the gamified
systems that are derived from loyalty
programs.
So here's an example that I picked out.
Almost at random from Nescafe Australia,
it's something called Cup Of Rewards.
Typical loyalty type program.
You get points for going to the site and
putting in a code because you've bought
certain Nescafe products.
And you accumulate the points and then you
can exchange them for discounts and for
coupons to use on various other sorts of
products.
That's a virtual currency.
It's making those points tradeable and
redeemable for real world benefits, and
therefore, it works like a virtual good or
like a currency in another case.
The issue with a lot of these virtual
currencies though, as with many other
examples of gamefication in many other
examples of loyalty programs, is that
they're typically not built today with the
focus on fun.
With the focus on the design aspects of
effective gamification.
They assume that just the fact that you
can redeem these points for tangible goods
will be enough to motivate you to come
back and participate, and buy the desired
products.
But, as we've seen throughout this class.
Tangible rewards have serious limitations.
And to the extent that a virtual currency
is just a way to harness a gamified system
to tangible extrinsic rewards.
It has all the limitations that I've
already talked about,
B\ut it doesn't have to be that way.
These systems can be designed in ways that
focus on fun and that systematically are
designed to unlock intrinsic motivation
and that can also feed into the virtual
economic aspects of the system.
If designed well, these systems can have
the attributes of both gamification and
economics,
So, what does it take to design a
successful virtual economy?
The key.
Skill is balance.
I've talked about balance as one of the
attributes of game design.
It's ensuring the game is not too hard,
too easy, too fast, too slow, one side
doesn't always win.
But balance is also critical in economics,
because economics is about,
Not necessarily money, it's about
scarcity.
Anytime there is scarcity, people make
choices under those conditions of
scarcity, they will tend to exhibit
economic behavior. And scarcity is a
variable in a gamefied system that's
defined, at least at some level,3 by the
designe. And in any syste, where people
have the ability to use virtual goods or
virtual currencies, it's important to
ensure that there is the right level of
scarcity.
The designer has to constantly balance to
ensure that there's not too much money,
which leads to inflation and effectively
devalues the currency, or too little,
which is too hard to get.
This is a process that can be called using
faucets and drains.
Faucets are things that put money into the
economy and drains are things that take it
out of the economy.
I guess if its a drain then I should
probably draw it this way, as you're going
down the drain.
But there are ways of balancing how much
money there is in the economy.
They can also be called and sometimes are,
sources and sinks.
The design technique is to ensure that the
balance is right.
If you've got too much money in the
system, it won't be good or too little.
Recall when I talked about the game
Monopoly, that when you pass go, you get
$200.
That's putting money into the system.
When you want to buy houses and hotels,
which are very valuable things,
You have to pay money, and that takes
money out of the system.
And this is something that effective game
designers building games around virtual
economies have learned to do.
For example, in World of Warcraft,
Way back at the beginning of the class I
showed you a little snippet of my
character, and at the end of that clip, he
turned into a dragon and flew away.
Well, that dragon, something called the
Sandstone Drake, is something that's
pretty hard to get in World of Warcraft or
at least it was when it first came out.
But that's also, once you have the ability
to make it, really expensive to make.
And the reason is that, the designers of
the game were trying to balance with this
and other things the level of money in the
world.
And by creating something that's really
desirable, because it's rare and hard to
get, and therefore high-level players.
Ones you typically have a lot money are
going to try and get it and making that
thing really expensive, they create a way
of taking money out of the economy.
And therefore, ensuring that people don't
just get richer and richer to the point
where the system goes out of balance.
So, building a gamified system is about
ensuring than level of balance,
Wanting people to be incentivized to take
money out of the economy in the right
times and the right amounts,
And also putting enough money into the
economy so, things don't get too expensive
and too hard to purchase.
The final point I'll make is that there is
some real dangers in building these
virtual economies, even though they have
lots of potential benefits.
We're talking about systems that may
involve real money or real tangible goods
as rewards and those are costly.
And, so, organizations setting up gamified
systems that have these attributes need to
make sure that they understand what kinds
of obligations they're taking on.
Secondly, they tend to be tangible
extrinsic rewards.
So all the concepts that I talked about
earlier, about the hedonic treadmill
effect,
Where rewards start to become less and
less desirable and the crowding out
effect, where people actually become less
motivated for the activity itself, because
they think it's so tied up in the reward.
All that's very relevant and an important
caution to think about when building
systems that have virtual economics in
them.
You don't wanna build a system that falls
into the trap of these tangible extrinsic
rewards, demotivating the enjoyable
behaviour.
In order to ensure that the intrinsic
motivation is still there,
It's important to think about, the
scarcity and rarity and surprise value of
the virtual goods.
If something feels cool, not necessarily,
because it's valuable in a tangible sense,
but because it's something that's
difficult to achieve, like that dragon in
World of Warcraf or it's really
interesting, and, looks great within in
the gamified system.
That might be something that still feels
valuable to the players, even though, or
basically, independent of the tangible
value associated with it.
So, there's much more that I could say
about designing virtual economies.
I wanted to put this unit in though, just
to ensure that you think about the
potential of this as one technique to
employ in gamefied systems or other kinds
of game-like systems,
But always be sure to do it in a way
that's cognizant of all of the points that
I made elsewhere in the course.