You can find fun in unexpected places. So,
here's a few examples about how to gamify
things that might not necessarily seem
like great candidates. Volkswagen had a
wonderful campaign called The Fun Theory,
and I've already given you one example
from that contest. The winning entry
called the speed camera lottery. Where
people would drive by a camera and if you
weren't speeding you'd automatically be
entered into a lottery and win some of the
money collected from the people who were
speeding. But that competition that
Volkswagen did had a variety of other
entries as well as some examples that
Volkswagen themselves came up with through
their marketing agency. So I'd like to ask
you to go and look at the fun theory
website and check out some of the
examples. In particular, look at the piano
stairs, where they created a playing piano
on the steps coming up from a subway stop
and the fact that you could walk up and
play the piano was so fun that many more
people chose to do that as opposed to take
the escalator next to it, good for those
people. They get more exercise because
they're having fun. Or the world's deepest
trashcan where they instrumented an
ordinary trashcan with sensors so that
when you threw some trash in it, you'd
hear a sound [sound]. [sound] As though it
was a deep cavern that you were throwing
something into. Again, people found that
kind of fun, and they were curious about
it, and that fact alone encouraged more
people to throw their trash into the trash
can. Good result. So go look at the Fun
Theory website, and try to familiarize
yourself with some of the different ways
to make fun that don't obviously seem like
they're good candidates. I'd like to give
you one other example and this is
something that may seem so basic and
simple, and dull frankly that it wouldn't
lend itself to fun but it was a case where
a little bit of game thinking went a long
way to generating real business results.
And it comes from LinkedIn, the business
social networking site. So on LinkedIn you
fill out a profile. Y ou describe your job
history, your employment, your skills.
There's places where you can put in
references from other people. And, all
sorts of details that are relevant to
understanding your capabilities for jobs
or other business opportunities. It's
important to LinkedIn that you fill in
your profile as completely as possible.
First of all that means you're more
committed to the site. And you may go for
some of their paid services. Second of
all, it makes it easy for other people to
find you and search on you, and therefore
makes it easier for you to network and get
some of the benefits that LinkedIn wants
you to get as a way of selling you, again,
their various kinds of services. And
finally, more data means more that
LinkedIn can search and analyze in order
to understand patterns in their users and
target you more effectively. So they want
you to fill in the profile in every
possible detail. But, filling out profiles
is pretty boring. Hard to think about how
to make that fun. Linkedin though, came up
with a way and it's not the way that you
might think in terms of creating some
profile game where you get points and
badges for filling out your profile, nope.
It was something much simpler. It was
this, the profile completeness bar. Took
about an hour for someone to code and
putting into the Linkedin system and it's
pretty simple. It just says here's how
much of your profile you filled out. In
this case, 90 percent and here's some
advice about how to fill it out more. Now
is that a game? No, not really. It doesn't
have the kinds of rules and the kinds of
objectives that we might think of as game.
It's also just so simple that no one would
really say, you are going to sit sown and
play the profile bar completion game
against someone else or against yourself.
It's just not that interesting. But it's a
little bit fun. It's a little bit
game-like, and just enough to encourage
people in meaningful ways to fill out
their profiles more. Because it turns out
that when LinkedIn put this profile bar
in, this very simple little [inaudible]
feature change that they added to their
service, profile completeness went up by
twenty%. A material increase in the amount
of data people were putting in just from
this little progress bar. So, what is it
about the progress bar that's at all
gamelike and that gets people to respond?
Well, here's a few things that I might
point out. The first thing is feedback.
So, the progress bar tells you how far
along you are. Before you just saw your
profile where it was. However much you
filled out. Maybe there were some things
that were blank. But now all of a sudden
you see, "I'm, 90 percent of the way
there." And, when you fill out something
else. When I get the other recommendation
I'm gonna see 95 percent there. And the
bar will move a little bit further towards
the edge. Immediate real-time feedback
about performance. Very common and
important aspect of games. Here, feedback
just gives you a number, gives you some
information, doesn't enforce you to do
anything with it. But that's
psychologically creates a dynamic that
makes people more likely to progress. And
that's the second aspect of what the bar
does. It creates a sense of progression.
So now we're no longer just talking about
entering data, filling out forms. We're
now talking about moving from the
beginning to the end of a process. And
that there are various little things that
we can do that are steps along the way.
It's not just start with nothing and end
up complete. It's a process of moving
forward of completing this objective. So
even though nothing in the profile bar is
expressly telling you that and even though
no one would say "yes, I am excited about
achieving the objective or progressing to
the end of the profile bar" there's that
little pole, there's that little
psychological draw of wanting to progress
to the end of the game and that's the
final point completion. We know now how
far we are from the end and in this case I
am pretty close, look here's all it's left
for me to get to 100%, is this little bit
at the end of the bar. We like completion.
We like neatness. We like finishing up a
collection. It's something that, again,
psychologically we're wired to want to do.
And seeing visually, in a simple way, how
close we are to the end, again, just draws
us along subtly and imperceptibly to want
to reach that objective. So this LinkedIn
progress bar, as simple as it was, as
trivial as it may seem was enough to
actually drive real results. And that's
what gamification does. It doesn't require
you to create an environment where people
are enthralled, where they are totally
focused in, that this is the most exciting
thing in their life. Hey, it's great when
you can do that. But gamification is about
finding the fun, finding the game-like
aspects wherever they are, and using them
to create an environment that moves people
a little bit more towards an objective.