I've talked some now about what
gamification is and about what games are.
It's time to get into the challenge of
thinking like a game designer,
understanding problems through the lens of
what I call game thinking, the core skill
for gamification. And I'd like to start
doing that by posing a fundamental
question. Why gamify? Why would you even
think to take a site or a business process
and try to make it more game-like if
you're interested in some serious results
and achieving some real world serious
objectives. So, let's look at an example
and try to think about why gamification
made sense for this service. The example
is Dodgeball. Dodgeball was one of the
first successful smart phone applications.
It was developed by a group of graduates
from the Interdisciplinary Technology
Program at NYU. And these guys like to
hang around in bars. So they built an app
for people who like to hang around in
bars. Here you see a screenshot of the web
client and Dodgeball gave you this map
that showed you where you were and then
you could check in. And say, here I am.
I'm at this location right here. This bar
that's on this street. And then you can
see where your friends were. Where other
people were who were using the application
where they had checked in. And this got
some notoriety. Started to get some pickup
in New York and San Francisco and places
like that. And in fact, Google bought the
company. But, Dodgeball had a problem. The
problem was that it's a chicken and egg
situation. If lots of your friends are on
Dodgeball, and there's lots of check-ins
that you can find, then there's a great
incentive for you to check-in as well. You
want to get access to all the information.
You get a lot of value from seeing all of
your friends and you know they will get a
lot of value from seeing what you're
doing. On the other hand, if you go to
Dodgeball and there's a blank map, not too
much reason for you to bother checking in.
So, how does the service get to critical
mass? Get above that level where there's a
not, not enough acti vity to get people
involved. So, that was one of the basic
challenges that Dodgeball had. After
leaving Google, Dennis Crowley, one of the
founders of Dodgeball started a new
company, they had a fairly similar basic
structure. It involved going and checking
in on a mobile client at locations that
you would go to. But this time, his new
company, Foursquare implemented what we
would now call gamification. So think
about, why would Foursquare use
gamification? What are some of the aspects
of this service that we saw originally in
Dodgeball, that might lend themselves to a
gamified approach? There's a number of
different things that you might come up
with and there is clearly no right answer.
But let's think about some of the aspects
of this problem that might make
gamification appropriate. The first is
that Dodgeball had what we could call an
engagement gap. It needed to get more
people to engage within use the service
and making the service fun, making the
service feel more engaging and game-like
is certainly a powerful way to do that.
The second is that, Dodgeball didn't have
a lot of variety in it. Basically, it was
check-in or don't check-in and then again,
you could get some analytics or
information, as well as seeing where your
friends were checking in but there weren't
too many different things to do but there
weren't too many different things to do.
And when things are unitary like that,
where it's either do something or don't do
something, it doesn't tend to engage
people as much, unless there's some very
direct result that they get. If it's go to
this website, click a button buy this
product, then you can see the
relationship. But if it's not that clear,
if there's some value in the exchange but
it's not as direct having options, having
choices as we talked about in discussing
games with meaningful choices could
potentially make the experience more
popular. And the next is that Dodgeball
didn't really have any progression.
Check-in or not, you really didn't get
anywhere by virtue of what you d id. And
so, checking in the hundredth time was
kind of like checking in the first time,
again limited the motivation of players to
want to participate actively in that
system. The good news is that Dodgeball
was a very social application. It involved
relationships with your friends. And
social interaction is very powerfully tied
to games because we love to compete
against our friends. We love to
collaborate, and share, and team up with
our friends. We love to have status visa
vis our friends and also see what our
friends our doing. And so all of that is
potentially quite consistent with a
gamified approach. And finally, there was
an opportunity with a service like
Dodgeball to make the action a habit. If
you have to think each time, oh, I better
get out my phone and go and check-in,
you're not going to do it all that much.
If it's habitual, if it's just a natural
thing that you do, you just kind of
automatically when you go to a new bar or
a club or a restaurant or even one that
you've gone to many times before, you just
pull out your phone and check-in then
you're much more likely to do it. So the
challenge for Dodgeball and for its
successor, Foursquare was how to make this
action a habit. Something again that is
very well suited to games which create
this environment that encourages people to
come back and come back. So, those are few
of the reasons that I think gamification
seemed to make sense for Foursquare, the
successor service to Dodgeball. So let's
look at what Foursquare did. The most
prominent thing that it did was
implemented a concept called Mayorships.
So, if you check in the most times, out of
everyone who's checked in at that
particular location, [sound] you're the
Mayor on Foursquare. And here you see the
badge, badges is another aspect of
gamification in Foursquare I'll talk
about. This is the badge that you get for
being the mayor of ten locations at the
same time. It's actually the super mayor
badge. But it's a representation of that
achievement of becoming the mayor. And
Foursquare buil t a system that made it
very easy to notify your friends on
Twitter and Facebook that you've become
the mayor of a place, who you displaced as
the mayor. It created this friendly
competition which made the act of checking
in, something more fun and something that
had more of a reward to it. Not
necessarily a monetary reward, although
some venues do give incentives to people
who are mayors. But a reward in that you
see something and other people see that
you are on top when you become the mayor
of a venue. Simple but potentially
valuable use of gamification. And then
Foursquare built a whole other set of game
mechanics around this check-in process. So
this was a screenshot from the Foursquare
page of Dennis Crowley, the CEO of
Foursquare. And you see a variety of data
points about what he's done. And then here
on the right you see the badges. Badges
were an important element of what
Foursquare did. They allowed them to
create much more richness of the service.
Remember I said choises are important and
progression is important. Badges gave all
sorts of options. Again, it's still just
checking in but now checking in becomes a
much more variated kind of activity. It
depends where you check in. If you check
in at a certain place like a health club,
you get a badge. If you check into the
health club a certain number of times, you
get another badge. If you check in at, say
a conference, like South by Southwest,
there are special purpose badges you get
that you can only get there. So suddenly,
this one act of checking in, becomes
something that seems very rich and complex
and nuanced for the users. It also is
something that allows you to level up. So,
Foursquare implemented different levels
within their badges, so checking into an
airport gives you one badge. But checking
into twenty different airports say, gives
you a higher level of that badge which is
harder to get. And Foursquare also had an
independent leveling system based on
points for number of check-ins which you
see here. Dennis was a super user le vel
three when this screen shot was taken. And
these are all examples of game mechanics
built around the basic process of checking
in. Did it work? Well, Foursquare now has
over twenty million users. They've raised
over $70 million in venture capital,
valuing the company over $600 million and
they've successfully overcome challenges
from major companies like Facebook that
got into this social location marketplace.
Now, Facebook Foursquare still has a long
way to go and correlation isn't causation.
That doesn't necessarily tell us that the
game mechanics were the reason for their
success. This is something that will come
back to later. But it's worth thinking
about how the gamification that Foursquare
implemented ties back to the challenges
that they face. So, consider how
gamification addressed the engagement gap,
the desire for habit formation, the need
for more choices and more progression, and
taking advantage of the social dimension
of what Four Square was doing. That's the
kind of thought process that you need to
engage in, in approaching problems through
the lens of game design.