So, you've oriented yourself to thinking
like a game designer. The next step is to
focus in on some of the basic design rules
that go into good game design. The first
of these is the player journey. We've
talked about thinking of your customers or
your audience as players. Part of what
that means is realizing that the player is
engaged in an experience. The player is
going through a journey in playing your
game. And the game doesn't have to give
them a 3-D virtual environment, where they
are getting in a car, or on a horse, and
riding around a territory to have that
journey. The journey is the conceptual
path that they follow through the game.
Because you don't want your player journey
to be just a random walk, because you
don't know where the player's going to
get. And ultimately that becomes
uninteresting. You want the player journey
to have a beginning, a middle, and an end.
And ideally, those are in some sort of
progression. The player always starts at
the beginning. You want the player to get
to a point of mastery and to have that
journey be seamless. So, the first aspect
of the player journey is onboarding. So,
in other words, how to get the player into
the game as quickly and easily as
possible? The second aspect is
scaffolding. How does the game provide
training wheels if you will? Places where
the game makes it easier and overcomes
some of the complexity that otherwise
would get a user stuck. That otherwise
would have the player not realize what
they need to do next. And finally does the
game enable that player to get to mastery?
To get to the point where the player has
conquered and achieved some real skill.
Some real accomplishment within the
framework of the game. So, let's look at
an example of how this works in, and
actual video game. I'd like you to go and
play the first level of Plants vs.
Zombies. Many of you already have, Plants
vs. Zombies has been an extremely
successful casual game on mobile devices
and the web as well. And you can go and,
play the web-based version for free. And
aga in, just play the first easy level of
the game, and think about how does this
game do onboarding and scaffolding? It's
level one, so you won't be able to see at
that point but half the mastery. But what
are the things that the game does that get
users quickly into the game and make it
easier for them to make progress within
the game. Go check it out and then come
back. Okay. Hope you had fun with that.
So, how does Plants vs Zombies onboard you
and scaffold the experience? Here are few
things I've picked up. It gives you guides
which deliberately say, here's what you
should do. Go pick up this seed packet. Go
put this down on the lawn. It does that
sometimes verbally with a direct guide and
sometimes just by highlighting something.
The flashing that tells you intuitively,
this is where I should click, or this is
where I should put something. It gives you
express feedback. Good job. Reinforces
that you did the right thing. The game
also is dumb down. There's a limit of what
you can do. So, at this point on level
one, you get one lane of grass only, only
one place you can put your plant. Once the
game gets going, there's a lot more
choices that you have both in terms of
what plant to use and where to put it. And
if the game were just one kind of plant on
one lane of grass, it would be pretty dull
after a while, after just a couple of
levels. But starting off, you need that
simplification because otherwise, the
games quickly becomes to complex to
understand and similarly there is only one
kind of monster. The result of which is
that the game at this level is
unbelievably easy. You have to try very
hard. I know probably some of you did die
on that level because you deliberately
didn't put something down, but you have to
try hard to fail at that level. It's
almost automatic that you will level up
and get that reinforced minute feedback
and reward of achieving something at that
first level. And also you will become
educated and be able to move up to the
next level of difficulty. All of this is
without any kind of manu al. Think about
it. If you had to explain to someone how
Plants vs. Zombies works. There's your
house and there's these zombies that are
ambling towards it along different lanes
of grass. And you have to click on seed
pods and put different kinds of plants
down that shoot things at the zombies. And
you get sunflowers that capture sunlight,
and that gets you more seeds, and all
this. It sounds really weird, first of
all, and also kind of complicated. But the
onboarding process and the scaffolding
process of the game makes it easy in just
a few minutes for anyone to figure it out
and to get to the point where they can go
to the next level of complexity until
ultimately the training wheels come off
and the game gives you the full
experience. So, that's onboarding and
scaffolding. And then ultimately, the
challenge down the road is to keep the
game interesting to get the player up to
the level of mastery. The second key to
effective game design. Second design rule
that I'll talk about is balance. Games
have to be balanced. Not too hard. Not too
easy. Not too many choices. Not too few
choices. All kinds of balance that have to
be in the game. Also, not too easy for one
player and not too easy for the other
player. There has to be a sense of
competition that either player could win.
Balance is something that games need at
every stage. A game can start off in
balance and then quickly become imbalanced
and then fall apart. So, a lot of game
design is about ensuring that the game is
constantly in balance. It's tricky,
because the players are real people. You
don't know exactly what they're going to
do. You have to play test the game to see
what happens and ensure that the game
doesn't get out of balance because at that
point it's not fun for at least one of the
players. So let's think about a game that
you may have played. The game being
Monopoly. You see it back there behind me
on the shelf. And in Monopoly, you go
around this game board that has four
sides. And it's divided up into various
tiles. And th ere are properties and
things like railroads and utilities and
places you draw cards and so forth, at
different places here on the board. And
all of those things have prices associated
with them or at least the houses do, and
the properties do, and they vary. So,
think about it. What if Boardwalk is our
call Boardwalk is somewhere down over
here. If Boardwalk costs twice as much,
how would the game change? Well it would
be a whole lot better if you owned
boardwalk and a whole lot worse if you
didn't. And it's impossible for me to say
in the abstract, is the price of Boardwalk
too low or too high. But if you play the
game enough times, you will find out at a
certain price, it's too high. The game is
ultimately not going to be fun for whoever
doesn't get Boardwalk, that's just a
matter of chance. The game will be out of
balance. So, with all the properties in
the game the challenge is keep the numbers
in balance so that it's fun for people to
play and also people of different skill
levels. The other piece of balance which
is not quite so obvious is this square
right here. Which in Monopoly says, go on
it. And as you probably know if you played
Monopoly, when you pass Go, you get $200.
Whoopie for me, I get $200. Why is that in
the game? Why is the game has to give you
money. The reason is balance. The reason
is that if money were not continuously
injected into the game, the players would
quickly run out. There's not enough money
built into the game to keep it going,
given all the properties you have to buy.
And if the game started you off with two
or three times as much money as you
started with, then the game would be too
easy. So, the game has to keep the economy
in balance. It's like a real economy.
People are buying things and people are
getting money and if the, balance between
those two things gets out of whack, we
have inflation. Or it becomes too
difficult for people to buy things, and
then we have something like a recession.
So, the game of Monopoly has to maintain
balance in the virtual economy b y
interject, by injecting $200 Into the
economy each time you pass Go. That's the
function of that within the game, it's all
about balance. So, same thing in
gamification. If you're trying to
encourage people to do something on your
website or trying to encourage your
employees to engage in some practice, it
needs to always be designed in a way
that's not too hard, not too easy, doesn't
necessarily favor one group systematically
over another. Third design rule for
gamification is to create an experience.
And this is at some level implicit in the
notion of gamification being about games,
but you want to take something that is not
game-like and make it feel game-like by
creating an integrated experience. So,
here is turntable.fm, a site that lets
people listen to music. Well, that's a
common thing on the web. But what
turntable.fm did in very clever ways was
essentially gamify this experience. So,
you go to this website, and there's some
music that's playing here, here's the, the
song that happens to be playing. But in
addition to the music itself that you
hear, you see this interface. You see a
group of people up at the top here who are
DJ, they're picking the music that gets
played. And then all the other people are
out here and you see these little very
simple avatars of their backs, they're
standing out there, they're in a club. So,
now all of a sudden you are not just
listening to music, you're in a club. And
you're in a club with a friend, a bunch of
friends. And you're in a club with a bunch
of people. Actual human beings here who
are picking the music. And you can rate
the music on this little thing down here
which lets you say the music is either
awesome or lame and then it gets a score
on this meter here. Of all of this
combines to reinforce the notion that your
involved not just in sitting and listening
to music in your home, but an experience
that you are in a particular kind of world
that means something and that makes the
act of listening to music somehow richer
and deeper then just going into IT unes
and clicking on one song or another.
That's a good example about how to use
gamification to change an experience
without really changing it. All
turntable.fm does is allow people to pick
music and other people to go into
different rooms to listen to it, but
they've created a game-like experience
around it that somehow makes it more fun
and engaging.