I've been talking about game thinking and
very clinical or structural terms, very
process oriented. It's important though,
as you're doing that, not to lose sight of
what really makes games engaging, the
emotional component of the experience.
And, we can represent in one very short
word what it is that makes games engaging.
Games are engaging because they are fun.
Fun is a word that we use to represent
what it is about things like games that
makes them good, makes them wonderful that
engages us that makes us want start to
playing them and want to keep playing
them. Fun is a hard word to get your arms
around kind of like games. But, as we are
able to define games we will be able to
define fun at least define some aspects of
what makes things fun. The starting point
is a quote from the great philosopher,
Mary Poppins who noted that in every job
there is to be done, there is an element
of fun. You find the fun and snap, the
job's a game. Important point here, notice
what she's talking about. She's talking
about, jobs. She's not talking about
playtime. She's talking about how to make
things that you have to do fun. And, of
course, in the context of the play, that's
an important lesson that she's teaching,
but it points up something very
significant. Fun is not limited to
recreation, fun is not limited to
entertainment, fun is something that we
can enjoy at work. It's something that we
can enjoy in all sorts of contacts and
therefore when we think about
gamification, think about making work or
social impact or behavior change seem more
engaging in game like it's essential to
think about how to make it fun. But the
question is what's fun. So think of it
yourself. What are some of the kinds of
things that you feel are fun? I'm not
saying an activity, I'm not saying that
you think it's fun to jump out of
airplanes or something like that. What are
the categories of emotions or the
categories of experiences that you would
think of as fun? Try to think about as
many different possible ones as you can
and think about how th ey relate to
different kinds of fun. Here are some
things that I've come up with that are
fun. Winning. All right, that's an easy
one. Many games have the idea of winners
and losers, and certainly winning is
something that we think of as fun, but
it's not the only thing. Problem-solving.
Sometimes the fun comes in overcoming
obstacles. In surmounting challenges,
whether we win or not, even if the
activity doesn't have the notion of a
winner. Just solving the problem,
achieving something that, in itself is
fun. Or sometimes just exploring, just
finding something new feels like fun to us
whether or not it's embedded in some kind
of challenge or some kind of game that has
winners or losers. Or what about just
chilling out. Lying on a beautiful beach
in the sun relaxing, at least for me, is
fun. Even though it doesn't have any of
those other attributes. Teamwork. We are
hardwired as a species to enjoy
collaborating and cooperating with others.
Working together as a team to achieve a
goal independently feels like fun.
Recognition. Now recognition is little bit
like winning, but it's not some objective
standard that says you have been
victorious in the game, it's someone else
has told you that you did a good job.
That's fun, that's feel good, whether or
not it means you have won the game.
Triumphing. Now here I'm talking about
something that is similar to winning, but
that has a particular aspect of it of
which is you win, and someone else loses,
vanquishing your opponent. Some people
find that independently fun, above and
beyond the joy of winning, the notion that
you've crushed someone else. Collecting We
find it fun to assemble things together
into collections. That's why some people
love to collect antiques or certain
categories of objects, and we find this
more generally in games when [inaudible]
people have an opportunity to assemble a
bunch of things, even if that's not an
express objective of the game, people do
it voluntarily because they find it fun.
Surprise. There's something fun about
being surprised. Why [laugh] do we love
[laugh] surprise parties? Because the idea
of surprise, of some novelty, something we
didn't expect, is independently fun. And
this will tie in later on when I start to
talk about psychology, the way that our
brain actually releases the chemical
dopamine when something is unexpected. And
the reward that we get is one that we
didn't anticipate, more so than if it's
the same reward that we expected.
Imagination. Daydreaming is fun. Just
thinking about ideas and imagining
something in your head has an element of
fun in and of itself. Sharing. Being
altruistic is fun. People feel good when
they give money to charity, again,
something that we are hardwired to think
about as a species. Now, it doesn't mean
that every time we share, it's fun, and
everyone shares everything all the time.
Anyone who has kids knows that getting
them to share is not always an easy task.
But there is an element of fun in the act
of altruism or sharing or giving someone a
gift. Role playing. We love trying on
roles. We love pretending that we're
someone else inhabiting another character,
whether that's all the way at the level of
a role playing game, where we are playing
a night elf druid or something to that
effect to the more lightweight ideas of
imagining ourselves in someone else's
shoes. Customization. It's fun to be able
to make something our own. It's fun to be
able to decide exactly the color that you
want for every aspect of the Nike shoes
that you buy. We love to be able to
personalize and customize things. And
finally, goofing off. There's something
fun about just letting it all hang out
about exploring the opportunity to just be
silly. All right. So, think about, for a
game or for a business process, or some
objective that you can imagine, or
perhaps, some of the ones that we've
already covered in the course, how you
might use the different kinds of fun that
we've identified, to produce an emotional
response to engage people in the activity.
And then next, we'll look a little more
systematically about how game designers
understand the concept of fun.