Now that I've introduced the concept of
fun, let's look more systematically
because knowing that there are many
different things that can produce fun
doesn't necessarily mean tell us as much
as we need to know to apply the concept
of fun in either game design or
gamification.
Nicole Lazzaro is a researcher and game
designer who has a firm called XEOesign,
and she has specialized in emotion in
games.
She's actually done foundational research
tracking people's eyes and faces and
looking at what in games actually
produces fun, and you can find out more
of her research on her website.
I put a link here to an image file that
provides much more detail, as well as the
original white paper that describes her
findings.
Lazzaro talks about four keys to fun,
four different kinds of fun that are
general categories that appear in any
kind of game-like context.
So, what are they?
The first is easy fun.
Fun that's about blowing off steam.
Just chilling out, goofing off, hanging
out with your friends.
It doesn't have to be taxing.
In fact, you don't want it to be taxing.
It's fun just because it's casual, it's
light, it's nice.
It's fun because it's easy.
Second category is just the opposite.
It's hard fun.
So, how can fun be hard?
Well, as I've talked about challenges,
problem solving, mastery, completion,
overcoming obstacles, all of these things
are fun in their own right.
So, we think of those things as fun
because the fun represents
accomplishment.
It represents overcoming something and
that's what makes the activity fun if
we're able to reach that plateau.
So, second category is hard fun.
Third category is people fun.
I guess I underlined the other one so I
underline easy as well.
The fun of interacting with others, the
fun of working together on a team.
The fun of socializing, fun that requires
other people.
Now, that could wind up being hard fun or
easy fun as well, but this differentiates
out the aspect of that fun that comes
from the social interaction.
And finally, there is what she calls
serious fun.
Well, fun can be hard.
How can fun be serious?
I thought serious was the opposite of
fun.
Not really.
First of all, some kinds of fun tie into
serious real objectives.
So, I talked about the fun of giving to
others, there's a fun in doing things
that are meaningful.
There's a fun in doing things that are
good for the planet, good for the family,
good for your community.
There is also a fun in doing things that
have a meaning for you.
So, you recall that when I talked about
some of the aspects of games, the magic
circle, and so forth, part of what makes
something game-like is that some
objective that has no real outside
purpose has a purpose within the game.
And it becomes engaging because, in the
game, that's meaningful to you.
So, this relates to fun as well.
In particular, when we're talking about
things like collections, pulling together
something, getting a whole bunch of
badges to unlock some sort of award, is
fun because it's meaningful in some
serious way for you at that time.
It may not be something that someone else
finds fun or meaningful but for you there
is some objective involved, some meaning
involved.
And so, Lazzaro would call that serious
fun.
Four different kinds of fun.
All different and not necessarily
mutually exclusive.
So, the same game may be one or more of
these things.
The point is, when we think about fun, we
can't limit ourself to just focusing on
one aspect or another.
If we think that fun is just something
easy and casual, we'll miss the
opportunity to engage people and make
things fun using some of these other
categories.
Now, other game designers that come up
with their own frameworks, one of them,
that's fairly well-known is from a game
designer named Marc LeBlanc who developed
a framework, that I'll talk about a
little bit later, for conceptualizing
games.
And as part of that, he came up with 8
different kinds of fun, slightly
different template than what Lazarro
talked about.
I won't go into these in detail but just
to get you thinking about different ways
to structure, thinking about fun.
LeBlanc talks about the 8 as sensation,
fantasy, narrative, challenge,
fellowship, discovery, expression, and
submission.
That last one, submission, is just the
casual kind of fun, just something as a
pastime.
And if you really want to dig into what
fun means for game design, I recommend to
you a book by Raph Koster, A Theory of
Fun for Game Design.
A classic book talking about how game
designers can think about fun and apply
it.
It's very conversational, gets you
thinking.
So, if you're looking for something else
to dig deeper, that would be a good place
to go.
Alright, so some takeaways.
What do we learn from this extended
discussion about fun?
Three things that I would have you take
away from this.
So, first is should go without saying,
fun doesn't just happen, it has to be
designed.
I'm going to talk later in the course
about design frameworks for gamification.
And it's really important to understand
that fun is not just something that's out
there in the world.
Sometimes, things just happen to be fun.
But if we're talking about making
something game-like, about motivating
people to go and use less electricity,or
to go and spend more time on your website
or to go and work together on a team to
solve a problem on a project at work, we
have to build systems that are expressly
designed to unlock these different
aspects of fun.
Second is, fun isn't always easy, fun
isn't always simple, fun isn't always a
purely happy positive experience.
Fun can be hard, fun can be challenging,
fun can be serious.
And we tend to ignore that when we're
thinking about fun, we shouldn't when
we're designing gamified systems.
Finally, there are different kinds of
fun.
Whether you take Lazzaro's four or
LaBlanc's eight or some other template,
the point is fun is a very nuanced
concept.
And we should look to exploit as many
kinds of fun as possible.
It's not always the right answer or the
best answer to focus in on one kind of
fun because we're missing opportunities
to make things fun in different ways.