How can gamification be applied in a way
that makes people happy? Fulfilled?
Flourishing individuals? To answer that
question, we need to look to the
discipline of positive psychology.
Positive psychology was developed most
notably by Martin Seligman who's at the
University of Pensylvania and also by
Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi. And I put his
name up there on the slide because that's
the only way that you're going to be able
to spell it. And, the idea of positive
psychology is that psychology generally is
about pathology. Is about what happens
when something goes wrong. Someone has
some abnormal mental situation that
doesn't allow them to think straight or
they're depressed. Or they are psychotic
in some way. And the question that
Seligman started asking was, well, why
don't we look at the opposite? Why don't
we look at what makes people happy and
fulfilled? Why don't we look at what
things it takes to make people feel better
about themselves and to feel like they
have authentically happy, flourishing
lives, as opposed to just what happens
when something goes wrong. And so that's
what the discipline of positive psychology
looks at and it's the basis of large
volumes of research into many different
areas. It turns out that much of this is
very relevant to understanding the
implication of games and thus by extension
certain kinds of gamification. Jane
McGonigal in her book, Reality is Broken,
points to Seligman's work and in some of
her later presentations points to how
games directly can address all of the
elements of his framework for human
flourishing, which he calls PERMA, which
stands for Positive emotions, Engagement,
Relationships, Meaning, and Achievement.
And I won't go through each of them in
detail, but it should be obvious how each
of these elements, which Seligman says are
the five core aspects of being a
fulfilled, flourishing individual. Not
just happy in a kind of light short term
sense but truly successful as an
individual. It turns out that all five of
these elements clearly tie i nto things
that we've discussed as core elements of
games. Most of which, gamification, if
it's done right and thoughtfully, has some
opportunity to tap into. So, that's the
high level way that gamification and games
can actually promote human flourishing.
But I want to specifically talk about the
concept of flow, which is what the
Csikszentmihalyi's major contribution
because that ties in even more directly to
some of the game design concepts that I
have discussed around gamification. The
idea of flow is that there's a state that
we sometimes get into where we are so
engaged in what we are doing. That, time
seems to lose its meaning. We lose our
self in the activity. We are fully and
completely engaged to the fullest our of
our abilities. It's a state that is
wonderful. And it's a state, interestingly
enough, that occurs at least as often, in
work activities as it does in
entertainment or play activities. And
Csikszentmihalyi started many years ago to
investigate this kind of flow, they did
all sorts of situations. In musicians and
rock climbers, and financial analysts,
lots of people who have the same
characteristic kind of experience. And he
developed a set of theories around what it
takes to get into the flow state. Now,
it's not something that you can do
automatically and directly. You can't say,
all right, I'm going to go into flow now.
It's something that happens organically
when an activity has certain
characteristics that are at a sufficient
level for that individual. But we can
think about what the characteristics are
of allowing flow to occur in a way that's
useful for games and gamification. So,
Csikszentmihalyi presents a chart that
looks at over time. What is the difficulty
level of a certain activity? How
challenging is it? And the idea here is
that, if the activity is too difficult up
here, it creates anxiety. It's too tough,
we can't succeed at it, it scares us off.
We get anxious about the activity. On the
other hand, if it's too easy, we get
bored. Something that is way below o ur
activities is a sure recipe for boredom.
In the middle is what Csikszentmihalyi
talks about as the flow channel. So, if we
stay between these two boundaries and have
an activity that over time is constantly
not too easy, not too hard, that's where
we have the opportunity for flow.
Specially if our movement through this
channel is variable. If it's an
interesting activity that maintains its
challenge, it's not something that we just
get on autopilot and do. The challenge
ramps up as we move along but the system
is designed to keep adapting so we never
go either too hard or too easy. So, that's
a key to achieving this notion of flow.
And therefore in game design, game
designers think a lot about tuning the
system so that for players it's neither
too hard nor too easy and yet it keeps
inter it remains interesting and variable
throughout the process. To get to a few
more aspects of flow that Csikszentmihalyi
talks about, that are relevant here for
games and gamification, he says, flow
occurs when there are clear goals. And
we've talked about this in terms of the
fundamental definition of games and we've
talked about it in terms of the first
design criteria for designing a gamified
system. He, second he says, there needs to
be a balance between perceived challenges
and skills. That's the essence of the
chart I just gave you. But the important
thing here is to remember that these are
perceived challenges and perceived skills.
The game feels like it's just hard enough.
Whether it is in some objective way,
there's really no way to tell. The
question is, how do you feel about the
experience? And is it tuned in a way that
you feel like it remains habitually
interesting. And third, I've talked about
this a lot, feedback. Clear and immediate
feedback. And this is not feedback in the
pure behaviorist sense of you're just
learning from the experience and moving
along and creating an association,
creating some reinforcement. This is
feedback allowing you to get to the point
where you feel totally immersed in the
experie nce and have that wonderful
experience of flow. So, if you can
gamified systems to push more in this
direction, to activate the five areas of
flourishing that Seligman talks about and
to maintain the requirements for flow that
Csikszentmihalyi talks about, you will
create a system that is deeper and more
rewarding than any kind of extrinsic
external motivator can ever be.