For this final segment on design, I wanted
you to hear from someone who actually
works in the field of game design
professionally.
Amy Jo Kim is an expert in the development
of social architectures.
In addition to her game design work, she's
also an author, and the organizer of
workshops on applied game design and
gamification.
As you'll see from my interview with her,
many of her ideas track the concepts that
I've been discussing in the course so far.
>> Amy Jo, thanks so much for joining us.
>> My pleasure.
>> You're one of the first people that I
came across talking about using game
design in other contexts, way before
anyone was using the term gamification.
So, I'm curious what you make of the
current gamification phenomenon, both how
people are describing it and what people
are actually doing.
>> A great question.
So, to me it's a great wave of interest in
gaming that I think is happening because
of all the same reasons we see, you know,
how many people grew up with games, how
much the mechanics are now easier to use.
Some of them are getting standardized into
APIs and tool kits.
So, I see that there is tremendous
interest, and I love that interest.
I think the word gamification will end up
going away, and that this will be part of
the tool kit of many different types of
design in the similar way that AI went
away.
We don't think of Amazon as an AI system,
although it does have what used to be
called artificial intelligence in it with
its collaborative filtering mechanisms,
right?
>> Mm-hm.
>> Evolution, I think, will also happen
with gamification.
I think what we see right now is the
awakening of what will be a much bigger
and longer trend, and I don't think it
will be called gamification cuz I don't
think it'll be one thing.
I think it will be many different
techniques that are inspired by games,
that get embedded in different ways in
software.
So short answer is, I think the word will
go away but.
The wave will only grow bigger and will
become an integral part of most software.
>> Well so let me ask you about something
specific that we hear a lot about in, in
gamification circles which is Richard
Bartle's notion of player types.
That, you know, pretty much every
presentation that, that I've heard on
gamification that goes into detail says
that, that the core issue is that there's
these, these different kinds of players
and we can design for them.
You actually I think have a, have a
slightly different perspective on that.
Can you talk about it?
>> Well I have a game designer's
perspective.
I know Richard Bartle.
I know where those come from.
And I also can, you know, repeat some of
what he said publicly which is, taking his
structures and applying it to all
gamification is silly.
And the reason is the, that's a model of a
certain kind of emergent human behavior
that he saw as a pattern in a number of
MUDs, multi-user dimensions, which are the
text precursors to games like W.o.W.
So, that is very true and when I worked on
designing MMOs, I worked on Ultima Online,
I worked on Earth and Beyond, done Sims
Online.
Those were particularly useful player
types.
There are many systems.
There's the, you know, Myers Briggs
system.
That's another system for in-, there's all
kinds of systems to say here's how people
are.
Systems are for utility, but they never
describe the be-all and end-all of all
human behavior.
So, if you're building an MMO or something
that has those dynamics, those four player
types are extremely useful, and I think
appropriate to use as a model.
You're working on something else, which is
what most of gamification is.
Then.
They actually don't work.
And the reason I know this is because I
have a consulting business and I've had,
you know, used player types with what,
maybe twenty maybe 30 different clients,
and what I've learned is that they only
work for a small segment of games.
A game like Structures.
I've developed a different take on player
types that is much more about what I see
in social media and social gaming, very
similar to Bartle, inspired by Bartle.
I always start by saying, there's Bartle's
player types.
Here's why they don't work for what we're
doing.
Here's how to tweak them to make them work
for what you're doing.
So here's Bartle's player types, and what
I've found and what he's said publicly is
that points, badges, levels, and
leaderboards which are the tropes of
gamification fundamentally appeal to
achievers which is a small segment.
And here's my take on Bartle's which I
call, which I structure around social
engagement verbs, because it's actually
easier to apply.
Very similarly, there's competing,
collaborating, exploring, and expressing.
Explore is right out of Bartle, so that
one is similar.
Competing is similar to the achievers, but
more specific.
Collaborating is very much what he calls
socializers, but with a very game
perspective.
And the reason is that if you're trying to
choose which game mechanics and which
strategy to adopt for your gamification.
Understanding this is extremely useful,
and then what Bartle didn't talk about at
all that is a huge driver in social media
and social gaming is self-expression.
That one was missing.
And the drive toward self-expression.
For many people, that's a primary player
type.
That there's people that will just play
with their avatars and their Miis on the
Wii and it's a very, very much a part of
how social games in particular monetize.
So these are the four words that I find
particularly useful.
And then here's very specific words, built
around those and one of the exercises that
I do with my clients is to map out the
core actions in their product against this
chart and see where they fall.
And then map that against who they're who
they're trying to reach.
For example, if you're trying to reach
females.
You always ask at the beginning who's
participating in this and how is it they
like to engage.
You're doing, if it's an all male
situation and let's say it's a bunch of
sales guys, they're gonna be really
compe-, really comfortable with friendly
and a competitive trope.
If it's females, predictably say middle
aged moms, or young moms, in general,
they're gonna respond much better to
collaborative mechanics and social
mechanics.
And things like the leader board would be
not the first thing to do for that kind of
community.
What I encourage all my clients to do and
my students to do, is to take this and
don't be afraid to tweak it.
Take it as a starting point.
Take Bartle as a starting point, and then
say, okay, in the world I'm living in with
my product, what, you know, what describes
the prototypes?
There might actually be something that's
much more specific.
>> Mm-hm.
>> To what you're doing that is more
useful to you.
So, the sac-, don't hold the sacred cow so
sacred.
>> [laugh].
>> Would be my summary statement.
>> So, always, always good advice.
So, let me ask you to say a little bit
more about collaborative gaming, because
people often tend to assume that, that
competition is just inherently something
that's at the part of games.
So, what's the opportunities base around
those more collaborative and
self-expression types of games?
>> Here's a particular definition that's
taken from one of the earliest books on
game design.
A game is a system where players engage in
an artificial conflict, by my rules,
resulting in a quantifiable outcome.
So that defines a whole host of games.
But not all games, and increasingly not
the games that in fact are being some of
the biggest hits in the gaming world.
So what that does define very well are
zero sum games.
And in game theories there are some games
are simply games where we are opponents,
where we competing for scarce resources,
if I win you lose.
You can layer a team dynamic on to that,
but that's fundamentally what a zero sum
game is.
Dynamics of.
Head-to-head battles.
Any kind of battle.
Any war simulation.
Go, chess, polo, anything like that.
Any rank ordered competition, the
Olympics.
These are all zero-sum games.
Most gambling games are also zero-sum
games.
Though you're usually playing against the
house.
But again its a finite pie that needs to
be divided up among winners and losers.
So, the, what I've found and some of the
games I've worked on that I love the most.
I found that their, that definition wasn't
working.
I worked on The Sims and then The Sims
Online, worked on Ultima Online.
I worked on Rock Band, probably one of my
favorite all-time experiences.
Those games, you can't just, they don't
have, The Sims doesn't have a quantifiable
outcome, you just keep playing.
Neither does Ultima Online.
So I define those games as a structured
experience with rules and goals that's fun
to play, which to me is a good working
definition of a gamified system.
Rules and goals are pretty critical, fun
to play is pretty critical, or at least
pleasant, engaging.
And not a completely unstructured
experience, but I realized as I dug into
game theory that, that actually was
defining, sorry, non-zero sum games.
In non-zero sum games we are not
opponents, we're partners.
And it's a win-win or possibly a lose-lose
situation.
Trading is a non-zero-sum game.
Draw Something is a perfect example of a
non-zero-sum game because you either both
lose or both win.
So other examples would be mini playground
games, party games.
I just mentioned Draw Something which is
Pictionary in a mobile device.
Martial arts are about personal
advancement and achievement but with a
very supportive your winning doesn't make
somebody else lose unless it's a
head-to-head competition.
The general martial arts is very
non-zero-sum.
And one of the best examples is a charity
walk where the more people you can join up
the more money you raise.
We're all winning together.
How many people can we bring in here to
win together?
That's really what non-zero sum gaming is
about, and to me that's the heart of
collaborative gaming.
Since you have experience both, on the web
side and in the, the games world, I'm
curious, if you feel like there is a
particular mistake that people make when
they come out of web design, and social
media, and those kinds of worlds, and try
to engage in gamification?
That's a great question.
The thing I see the most and I just saw
this last week when I did an audit for a
start up.
See it all the time.
People in the web world are very good at
understanding funnels and engagement
loops.
That's very natural.
That's familiar to a lot of what they do.
They also are familiar with loyalty and
the basic concepts of loyalty.
What they are not familiar with is the
fact that a gaming experience changes over
time, and that there are key stages of a
players life cycle what you call the
player journey, that require actually a
different set of features and a different
set of powers to give the person.
So the idea that you're creating an
experience that unfolds over time and
changes over time in response to someone's
increasing commitment and skill.
Is fundamental to a good game, especially
a good computer game.
And that's the mistake I see people
seeing.
They say look, we've got the funnel, and
we've got this habit loop built, and now
we will drive habits.
Well, you will for a little while.
And guess what, if you throw a bunch of
points at people you'll get a short term
lift.
I have no doubt.
And you'll see some nice metrics, but it's
not sustainable.
The thing that makes it sustainable is for
the experience itself to evolve over time.
So I use the three stages of newbie,
regular, and expert as an analytic tool to
help you really think about, you know, the
first day or week all of which is a newbie
experience, not just that very first
visit.
And then the 2-month-in when someone has
actually become a regular.
And then the expert, what we in gaming
call the elder game.
What is it that the most dedicated and
skillful two to five percent of your
players can do that everybody else can't
do?
What is it that keeps them hooked?
It's not the same thing as in an earlier
stage.
So really thinking about that life cycle
and thinking about your engagement loops
at every stage of your life cycle, not
just at that very first stage, will
dramatically impact your ability to drive
retention and profit.
>> Now that's, that's very good advice
and, and of course I think well, what
we're all looking for is ways to make this
sustainable and engaging.
So, very much appreciate you sharing your
insights with the class.
Thanks for joining us.
>> Thanks for having me.