If you've decided that gamification is a
good approach to use for your business
challenge, how do you ensure that you're
doing it in a thoughtful, deep,
substantive, meaningful way? The best way
I can think of to illustrate this is to
give you a detailed example of a service
that uses all of the standard PBL type
game elements but pulls them together in a
coherent and consistent way to address
some of the deeper aspects of game design
and psychology and ultimately meaning. The
site is called Stack Overflow. It's part
of a larger group of sites now called
Stack Exchange. And I'm going to
intersperse screenshots of the site with
some quotes from Jeff Atwood who's one of
the founders of the site from a blog post
that he put out trying to explain how and
why he and his co-founder made design
decisions to implement gamification. Now,
an important point he makes is that when
the site was setup, he had no idea what
gamification was. And all these decisions
were not made based on gamification being
an interesting or cool design practice.
They were ways that he and his co-founder
trying to solve the challenges that they
had in front of them which just happened
to be the kinds of things that we now
think about as gamification. So, Stack
Overflow is a site for programmers. It's a
question and answer site where you can go
to ask questions about how to write
software or problems that you're having
with certain kinds of coding. And, other
people answer the questions. Well, that
doesn't seem terribly interesting, does
it? Asking and answering questions about
coding. In particular, how do you get
people to spend their own volunteer time
answering other people's questions,
answering questions from total strangers
about how to code certain things. Well, it
turns out that Stack Overflow has been
tremendously successful at this very task.
The site or the collection of sites now
that they've put together, have over two
million registered users. They average
over 5,000 new questions per day and over
10,000 new answers per day on the si te.
So, they've been able to motivate people
to engage in this practice. And the
question is, how have they been able to do
that? Well, the first reason is by
thinking about the problem in the right
way. What is programming? Well, you can
look at programming as the example of
something very dull and rote. You can look
at answering questions about programming
as something inherently boring, and
difficult. Or you can look at it as
something cool and wonderful and magical
and game-like. And that's the approach
that the designers of the site took. So
Atwood says, "The field of programming is
almost definition, by definition one of
constant learning." Learning as we talked
about has a great affinity for games. And
he said, "Programming is, supposed to be
fun." Says who? Well, says them. And
obviously says a lot of other programmers.
And to the extent that you can take this
approach, and think of what you're doing
as fun, then it naturally leads towards a
gamified approach that's authentic, that's
not just based on how do we make people do
this thing which otherwise they wouldn't
want to do. How do we come up with a whole
bunch of rewards that we'll dangle in
front of people, a bunch of big carrots or
a bunch of bit sticks that will get them
to do the thing. This approach says, well,
how do we think about the problem in a way
that makes the people feel like they want
to do it themselves? If it is fun, if you
can find the fun in any problem as Mary
Poppins says, then snap, it becomes a
game, and people will want to do it
voluntarily. So, that's the first aspect
of what they've done. Second aspect of
what they've done, is to implement a
system that is reflective of their
community. Know your players. Understand
what the community is that's involved in
the activity. And this is particularly
important because meaning is socially
constructed in communities. What's
meaningful? What's important is not the
same from every community to every other
community. It depends on the norms of
those groups and communiti es and that
kind of activity they're involved in. So,
take Foursquare's badges which we've seen
before. Very colorful. Very fun, if you
will, creative, graphical lots of little
inside jokes here and things like pumpkin
and so forth. These are badges that are
designed to be cool in their own, right?
Which is part of, of the whole Foursquare
mantra when they implemented these
gamified elements to get people to think
that checking in was somehow something fun
that they'd want to do. The badges in
Stack overflow look quite different. So,
here's a profile page of a user. This
happens to be a very high-level user. In
fact, he's one of the moderators who have
the extreme privilege of helping to run
the whole site. He's got 88,000
reputations points which is an awful lot.
And here are his badges. Just that. 52
gold badges, 224 silver badges, 434 bronze
badges. So you notice a very different
aesthetic here. This is a site for
programers, for geeks. So, it's about lots
of numbers, lots of information and not
lots of visual clutter. But just get to
the heart of the information right away.
Gold, silver, bronze. What those badges
are and what they mean. So, at a glance
you can see what this person's reputation
score looks like. So, two different ways
to do badges. Each one is appropriate for
the situation at hand. So, this is an
example of a stack overflow set of
questions and answers, there was a
question above and here is an answer from
someone talking about how to do something,
and here's the person who gave the answer.
This user Bahbu, and you can see this
person has 204 points and nine bronze
badges, a pretty low level user. And then
here, someone else has come in. This other
user, and that person has edited the
answer. And you see this person is a much
higher level user. They've got 9,000
points and a bunch of gold badges and so
forth. Not quite at the level of Bill the
Lizard but a very much higher level user
and they have voluntarily edited the other
person's post. So, not o nly did that
person voluntarily come up with an answer,
they voluntarily modified and improved
upon someone else's answer. You see here
there's a, a link to improve the answer.
Well, that's really great. If the system
not only gets people to come up with their
own answers, but to improve that are
there, it's a self-reinforcing,
self-improving system. And here you see
another example of an answer that was done
by this person and then down below, some
dialogue back and forth by the person
doing the answer and the person posting
the question. Again, more information. The
question gets more precise. The answer
gets precise. More activity actually
improves the system. So, that's a really
great process. If you can design a system
that has those characteristics, it will be
very powerful. And the question is then,
so how does gamification do that for stack
overflow? Back to Atwood again. Stack
overflow, he says, is many ways my
personal Counterstrike. Now, Counterstrike
is a game, it was a modification of a game
called Half Life, which is an interesting
story in its own right. But the cool thing
about Counterstrike was that it was
structured around groups coming together
and having to fight as a team.
Counterstrike is a game where you're a
commando unit that's fighting against
terrorists. It's all about shooting at
things, using various different weapons.
But in Counterstrike, if you go off on
your own you're almost certainly going to
die. You need to group up with a bunch of
different people and some of them will
cover you as you move forward and will
take out snipers and so forth. You have to
work together as a team. And, that
activity is what made Counterstrike really
interesting and challenging for a lot of
gamers. Because it's harder to group up
with people and all work together as a
team than just to go off on your own. And
Counterstrike implemented this in a really
interesting and compelling way so it was a
extremely successful game. And what Atwood
says is that notion of working together as
a team. T hat to win the game you have to
be effective, not just yourself but as a
teammate, as a part of a larger whole, was
the lesson that he and his co-founder took
to apply to questions and answers for
programming. So, the idea is, helping
fellow programmers is the way that you win
at the game. You don't win by being
awesome by yourself. You win by helping
other people. So, the gamified system is
structured in Stack Overflow relentlessly
to incentivize pro-social behavior. To
incentivize things like, as we saw,
improving on other people's answers as
opposed to just doing stuff purely
yourself in a way that doesn't help the
group. So, let's look very quickly at some
of the ways that Stack Overflow structures
its game elements, to produce that same
Counterstrike like result, where people
are encouraged to work together in order
to win in the game. The first is that the
points in the system are actually called
reputation and the primary way you get
points is when your fellow users vote up
your questions and answers. So, not for
your actions but for other people saying
you did a good job. That's the core
definition of reputation in the system,
you have to do something other people
think highly of in order to get points.
Similarly, there is this structure in
Stack Overflow called bounties where you
can give reputation to someone for coming
up with an answer or good answer to a
question. That creates this notion of
exchange and gifting which is another very
powerful pro-social norm, that gets
activated by this game mechanic. So, all
of these game mechanics around the point
system are structured to reward not
individual achievement but things that
serve the collective good. And Atwood
talks about this as encouraging groups to
do what's best for the world rather than
their own specific selfish needs. Here, he
eludes to a wonderful article by Clay
Shirky called A Group Is Its Own Worst
Enemy, where Shirky points out that
there's this, there's this real problem
online, that we have really easy group
formation. You can form a g roup for
anything online, but the group tends to
fall apart because the group may have some
set of goals, there may be some set of
things that we can agree is in the group's
interest. But all the people who
participate in the group aren't the group.
They're individuals. And so they pull in
their own direction and the group, as it
grows, tends to fall apart and
disintegrate because it doesn't have
hierarchy and structure. The lack of
hierarchy and structure is what's great
about online activities and online groups.
But they cause attention. And Atwood's
claim here is that game elements, game
stack overflow are what pull against that
natural tendencies of groups to collapse
into selfish interests. So, for example,
the reputation gives you certain powers,
but they are not just powers to go off on
to different parts of the site and lord
over people, they're powers that give you
abilities to be, essentially, a moderator
of the site, to engage in more of this
beneficial behavior on the site. And
that's cool, that's something you get with
reputation, but it's also something that
helps others. Similarly, Stack Overflow
has a badge system. But again, it's not
the Foursquare type of badge system where
the badges are about showing off your big
cabinet with all of your cool badges in
them. The badges are about doing things.
Some of them are just things that are good
for the site, visit every section of the
FAQ. But some of them are about things
that are good for others. Edit 100 posts
that have been inactive. Actively that,
that's not really one but here. Vote 300
times. Leave ten comments and so forth,
all social behavior. And this is
especially true of the gold badges, the
really cool badges that people are going
to want, there you have to do things like
edit 500 posts. Remember, editing a post
is the thing that's most beneficial in
terms of improving the quality of the site
collectively. But the thing that people
are least likely to do on their own. So,
use a badge to encourage people to do it.
Similarly g reat answers get you a gold
badge but so do great questions and so do
questions that are famous that are viewed
by lots of people. So, all of these are
different ways of incentivizing the very
things that are in the interests of the
site, in the interests of the group as
opposed to just incentivizing the things
that make, make people feel individually
cool. And Attwood ultimately talks about
this as the game elements being in service
of a higher purpose. He said it ultimately
helps him become more knowledgeable and a
better communicator while improving the
very fabric of the web for everyone. Now,
not every gamified site can credibly claim
to improve the fabric of the web for
everyone. If it's purely a marketing site
that's trying to get more customers
engaged, it's hard to see this as
something that is fundamentally making the
internet a better place. It's not
necessarily in conflict with it. But as
long as you can push in that direction.
Try to find things that are meaningful and
fun for people, but also try to find ways
to have the gamification elements pushed
towards cooperation, collaboration and
larger good, larger purpose, that notion
of relatedness and self-determination
theory, the more likely is the gamified
site will be deep and significant and