I've thrown a lot at you in the course so
far. And truth be told, if this were say,
an enterprise workshop on gamification, I
would have stopped after the last section.
You've got all the basic concepts. You've
got a design framework. You've got all of
the components necessary to apply
gamification successfully. But because
this is a course, I want to go deeper. I
want to push you to think about some of
the conceptual issues around gamification
and some of the big, deep questions about
its future and about different ways to
implement it. And so, this is a good point
in the course to take stock. At a high
level about just what gamification is.
Because it turns out that, for many of the
reasons that I've talked about, there are
really two different kinds of
gamification. Two different things that
people mean when they use that word. Both,
to my mind, are true examples of
gamification and there certainly are
plenty of places which where they overlap,
some of which I'll illustrate but there
are very different answers that you get to
about gamification depending on which of
these two models you adhere to and people
use the same word gamification for both of
them and don't necessarily think about.
Which one they're following. The best way
that I can think of to divide these two
camps is to ask you the following
question. Is this a game? This slot
machine here which I've showed you before.
Is it a game? Well, if you use the
definitions of games that I gave you early
on in the in the course, probably not.
There's no sense of a game like or play
like attitude. There is no sense of
meaningful choices here. The slot machine
is just a big random number generator. You
pull the handle. That's it. And it either
gives you money or it doesn't. And whether
it gives you money or not is not based on
your skill and your play, it's just based
on a random, determination by the slot
machine itself. So, fundamentally, the
slot machine is no different then just
flipping a coin. Time after time after
time and seeing if you get heads or ta ils
and that's not really a game, is it? On
the other hand. Many of the examples we
have of social games, on social networks
online, as well as gamification, as I've
talked about, look a lot like the slot
machine. They create engagement loops
which pull in the user by the potential of
a reward. They involve surprise. They
involve trying to find a pattern. And many
people find them powerfully engaging in
many of the same ways that they find games
powerfully engaging. So there's something
game like. About the slot machine, and we
call it a game of chance. But that's very
different from most of the types of games
that I described early on in defining what
makes something truly game-like. And I
think this is indicative of a broader
split within the notion of gamification.
There really are two different things
going on when we use the term. One, thing
could be summarized as being about doing.
Gamification is about doing things using
games and game-like structures. The other
approach, I can over-simplify by saying
it's about feeling. It's about not
necessarily what you do, but how you feel
about it. What's going on inside you? And
this leads to a variety of different,
decisions that get made. Implicitly in
which camp you're in, so where do you draw
inspirations from if you're focussing on
doing things or getting other people to do
things then you'll draw from disciplines
like marketing and economics. Disciplines
that are about measuring behavior and
thinking about craving structures that
encourage people to behave in certain
ways. On the other hand if you come from
the feelings aren't we going to look more
to the things like game design and
cognitive psychology. These disciplines
that are about whats going on makes
someone interested in something, what is
there more deeply then. A surface
phenomenon that they're experiencing. And,
we've already talked about both of these
in the class, because the class is
designed to give you both perspectives and
show where they overlap. Similarly, if
you're thinking in the first cam p, you'll
talk about incentives, things that create
some mechanism to pull someone to an
activity. The other camp, you'll talk
about experiences. What the person
encounters, how they experience certain
activities again, the incentive is
something outside of them. The experience
is something inside them. The next one is
do we talk about satisfying people's
needs, people's desires, people's wants,
or do we talk about fun? That term that,
as we talked about, we can give meaning to
and we can think systematically about how
to design for fun, but it's something more
than just meeting basic needs or even
meeting higher level kinds of needs that
people have. There's something again
experiential and indivisible what this
notion of fun. If you are in the first
camp, you will gravitate more towards game
elements, which are talked about in great
detail, and I say here inductive, in other
words, the idea is. Building up from the
bottom, little bits and pieces of games to
move towards the more integrated
experience. If you take the other
approach, you will start with game
thinking which is more deductive. Starting
with general principals about how games
work and using those to go down to the
more specific examples. If you are in the
first camp you'll think more about status.
If you're in the second camp you'll think
more about meaning. And I've talked about
both of these in the psychological
section. The appeal of status but also
it's dangers. First camp is PBLs, points,
badges, leader boards. Second camp is
gamification as puzzles, as learning, as
challenges which can be represented in
systems involving game elements and
points, badges and leader boards but
typically involve a different kind of
approach. An approach that puts the
challenges and the puzzles and the
creativity at the center rather than the
structural or visible elements. Rewards on
the one hand, I've talked in great detail
about reward design. Especially in the
behaviorist tradition of psychology.
Progression, on the other hand. Mastery.
Competence. Not neces sarily about a
reward. More about the journey. And
finally and in summary. The first camp is
about making users do things. The second
camp is about making players awesome.
Making users do things should mean making
them do things that they want to do on
their own. But, somehow don't get to.
There are things that are beneficial for
the player but the player needs some
motivational help. To push them along that
path. It doesn't mean, necessarily forcing
someone or tricking someone into doing
something that they never really wanted to
do in the first place. Making players
awesome is about figuring out in the first
instance. What it is that will help that
someone achieve their full potential and
focusing more on that, focusing on the
users goal than the external goals of some
organization or company [inaudible] those
users. Now it should be evident by now.
That I tend to feel. Much more comfortable
with this camp here on the right with the
more game based approach to gamification.
But, I think it's important. And
essential, really to also understand the
one on the left. Many game designers tend
to be very dismissive or critical of
gamification. And we're going to look in
detail at some of those critiques later on
in the course. And I tend to think that
while their critiques do have some bite,
the notion that gamification is
fundamentally flawed. And looking for
example at game elements as opposed to
more integrative structures of game
thinking, is fundamentally misguided. I
tend to take issue with that because, as
we've seen, there are lots of great
examples of using the more doing based
approach to gamification to get to
valuable results for companies and for
users or players of the gamified system.
So, both perspectives tend to be valuable.
And, in a specific case, you may find one
or the other is more helpful. But it's
important to, as a starting point, be
aware of these two approaches and be aware
of where they come together and where they
diverge.