How do you decide if gamification is right
for your organization or the business
problem or other kind of challenge that
you have to address? There are four
questions to ask to determine if
gamification is a good approach to take.
And these are, first of all, motivation.
Gamification is about motivation so you
need to first say, would you derive value
from encouraging certain behavior if
motivation matters to the business
problem, it's likely the gamification
would be a good approach. Second is
meaningful choices. Are the tasks involved
potentially, sufficiently interesting?
Meaningful choices is one definition of
the very nature of games. And it's
implicit in many aspects of the intrinsic
motivation description that I gave you
under self-determination theory. The
notion of competence and autonomy is
basically the same as saying the user has
to feel like there are choices and those
choices are meaningful. Third is
structure. And this basically says, can we
effectively gamify the system by using
rules or algorithms? So, is this a problem
that will lend itself to a digital system,
which is what gamification typically is,
that encodes the basic rules for this
problem set? If it's not, if it's
something that's too vague or too
subjective or where the rules or the
objectives aren't sufficiently clear, then
gamification may not work even if this is
a problem that would benefit from
motivation and that's sufficiently
interesting. And finally, potential
conflicts. What other motivational
structures are there in the organization?
And, will the gamified system potentially
come into tension with them? So, let's
look at all four of those questions in a
little bit more detail. The first is
motivation. So, what are the situations
where motivation is important? Typically
two broad categories which is you see are
very different. The first is situations
that involve real deep creativity or
situations that involve unique skills and
connections and teamwork. Situations where
it's not just rote work. It's not
necessaril y something simple and
familiar. It's something complex and deep
that requires people to go the extra mile.
And motivation is the secret ingredient
that gets them to do that. So, these are
the high value add kinds of tasks, the
desire for innovation, the desire for more
productivity, the desire for lasting
consumer engagement. The things that
require more than just a simple push of
the button. The second broad category
where motivation is valuable, though, is
exactly that kind of situation. The
situation where the task at hand seems
very dull, boring, and repetitive. Because
those are the kinds of task where, if you
can find some motivation, if you can find
some meaning and some interest level in
the task and some challenge that motivates
people, the impact is quite significant
because without those things, there's no
way except for the external, extrinsic
kinds of approaches to get people involved
in the task. And a wonderful example comes
from the book Reamde, a recent science
fiction book by Neal Stephenson. If you
haven't read it, I'd encourage you to read
the first 200 pages, they're great. The
next 800 pages, not so good. But it's a
delightful book, like many of his books,
in terms of getting us to think about a
potential future that in many ways is
already here. And the example for
gamification is that one of the characters
in the game, excuse me, in the book, is
the CEO of a massively multiplayer online
games company vaguely like the company
that makes World of Warcraft. Only, the
business model for this game is using
gamification. Specifically the game
applies itself generates revenue by going
to organizations that have dull tasks. The
first example that they give is airports
dealing with security and having people
having to sit there and insure that no one
walks in the wrong way through the door
that goes to the baggage claim area.
Because there has to be an opening going
through there. And so therefore, you have
to check to make sure people aren't coming
through the wro ng way because they don't
go through security. And so, someone has
to sit there, but it's the most boring
thing in the world, to have to watch
person after person after person go out
the door on the off chance that some idiot
will wander in the other way by accident.
Much more likely to be that idiot than an
actual terrorist, but if that idiot gets
through because the person sitting at the
door fell asleep or wasn't paying
attention in their mind numbingly boring
task, then we've had lots of examples
where whole terminals have to get shut
down because someone is in the terminal
without having to gone through security
screening. So, the idea in Reamde, is that
this company comes up with the great idea.
They will use 3D motion capture to
represent the people walking through the
passage way in the terminal as creatures
in the game. So now, there's a castle in
the game and the people are walking down a
certain passage way in the castle, all in
one direction. But the game says, in the
game, that there is a goblin trying to
sneak in. And if you catch the goblin
trying to sneak in, you get a big reward,
lots of experience points for you in the
game. And the result is lots of players of
the game sit there and try to catch the
goblin. They try to find the goblin even
though it involves the same thing that the
security guard had to do at the airport,
sitting and watching person after person
going through the right way in the hope
that you might find someone going through
the wrong way. Putting it into the game
suddenly makes that fun and engaging for
people. And in the book, this becomes a
huge business opportunity for this company
because they're able to leverage the
engagement of the game players to do tasks
that otherwise would be deadly boring. So,
that's an example of one kind of task that
might lend itself to gamified motivation
that's very different from the kinds of
tasks that we might at first think of.
Second question to decide whether
gamification is right for you is whether
it involves meaningful choic es. And here,
we can think about a number of different
kinds of situations that we talked about
that make choices meaningful. Are there
options for the user? Do they connect up
with things that are meaningful for the
user? Does the gamified system do things
in a way that seem interesting where the
user has to make choices, that they care
about the outcome? But there are many
gamified systems out there today, that
don't seem to focus on this as much.
Here's one example here which is Google
News Badges which I believe I've already
mention. And Google News Badges gives you
badges just for reading stories on a
particular area. There's no choice
involved except for the choice of what
stories you're reading. But that's not
really a meaningful choice. Here you see
that this person started reading stories
about Syria and it says keep reading about
Syria and you'll earn a bronze badge. But
the question is, what's meaningful about
that? If you read a little bit about
Syria, do you want to start reading much
more about Syria to become an expert on
Syria? Or, do you want to read some about
Syria and then go read something about the
Olympics, or some other topic because
that's what a news site or a newspaper
does, it lets you find out about many
different things, as opposed to one thing
to the exclusion of all others. That's not
really a meaningful choice, deciding to
write, to read a few more articles about
something just because you're going to get
a badge. So, I don't wanna cast
dispersions at Google News badges. I'm not
sure what the design criteria were for it
and what it's trying to accomplish but
from a perspective of thinking about
whether this is a situation where
gamification is a logical or natural
solution, not so clear. Third one is
structure. Is about can we use rules,
algorithms, hard-edged decisions to
implement a gamified system. And so, here
is the Samsung Nation site that I referred
to a number of times. And you can see the
points in the leader boards, but the
question is un derlying that. What does it
take to get the points? What things are
worth more? So, two of the tasks that Sam
Sung Nation let's you address are sharing
things on Twitter, tweeting about
something you've done on the site or
registering your product that you bought,
your Samsung product that you bought in a
real store, do you go on the site and
register it? Samsung Nation gives you 500
points for registering the product and a
100 points for tweeting about something
that you did on the site. Now, I don't
know again from Samsung's business
criteria, why they picked one or the
other. But the point is a system that lets
you make those choices in trade-offs in a
coherent way, tends to be one that will
lends itself well towards gamification
because you can build in these different
kinds of motivators and then think about
different ways to encourage people to
chose between them and to make their own
trade-off as to what's more meaningful to
them. Again, this ties back in to the
notion of meaningful choices. The points
are just guides and people in playing need
to decide, how they personally value the
activity, vis-a-vis what the point system
is telling them. And finally, conflicts.
What other motivational structures are
there out there? So, this is particularly
important, say, in a company, there is a
motivational structure for employees. It's
called their salary. It's called their
desire not to get fired from their job.
That's not necessarily in conflict with
some system that says go do this because
it's fun and because it's going to
motivate you to be part of a community to
have some achievement or accomplishment.
But, there might be some tension if those
things pull in opposite directions or if
the user starts to wonder, well, should I
be doing this for the salary or should I
be doing this for the fun, what's the
trade off between the two? Another context
for illustrative purposes where this comes
up a lot is, school. So, we have all kinds
of motivators in school, including very
extrinsic ones, as well as increasingly
intrinsic ones trying to get students to
authentically care about and enjoy
learning. So , when gamification gets
applied to learning, it's very important
to try to understand the potential
conflicts. So, this here is a gamified
leader board or gamified experience point
system that was developed by Lee Sheldon
who's a professor at Rensselaer
Polytechnic Institute, he teaches game
design, and he gamified his courses. And
this was the system that he used for
giving students points instead of saying,
you get an A+ for a perfect score, and
then it goes down from there A, B, C, D, F
and the idea being you start at a 100
percent and every mistake you get, you go
down till you settle on your final grade.
What Sheldon realized was that games don't
work that way, games work by building up,
you start at zero experience points and
grow and grow and grow until you reach
your final level. So, he said, why don't
we do school like this, why don't we say
you start here at zero, you start with an
F? And based on what you do, based on
every assignment that you turn in, every
achievement you get within the course, you
move up and up and up until you ultimately
settle at your final level and that's your
grade. Very cool idea. Very powerful if
designed right. But, it needs to be
designed consciously around the existing
sets of incentives. So, if this system
were done in parallel to traditional
grading, that would cause some real
tension and some real dissonance for the
students. In Sheldon's class, as he uses
this as the entire grading structure. But
even so, it needs to be designed in an
effective way that doesn't create
conflicts between different other kinds of
motivations that students might have. So,
that's an example to illustrate the need
to think about different tensions that
might occur among different motivators. If
you think about all four of these
questions systematically and come up with
good answers for them, you can be fairly
confident that gamification is a
worthwhile approach to use to tackle a par
ticular business or other challenge.