You may not realize it from this course
but my degree is actually in law, and most
of my research work has been on legal and
policy aspects of the Internet and related
emerging technologies as opposed to the
more strategic and business oriented
aspects that were focused on this course
but the two things do come together. In
the discussion of legal issues around
gamification and while the primary
considerations in developing a gamified
system are not law so much. There are some
areas where legal and also regulatory
considerations could become important. And
so they are worth touching on in the
context of risks and concerns for defining
a gamified system. So let me quickly go
through five issues in which the legal
system could become a problem or you might
get sued by someone because of some issue
in a gamified system. The first is
privacy. One of the aspects of
gamification is that you're going to get
lots of information potentially about
players, information about who they are,
their profile and so forth, but also
tremendously granular data about what
they're doing. Every action they take in
the game potentially can be collected and
that's a great thing. That's the basis of
the analytic and the ability of a well
designed gamified system optimized for the
players interest and to provide real
learnings for the company that sets it up.
But the flip side of that is the developer
of the gamified system is going to have
tremendously detailed and personal
information about the players. And that
necessarily brings it to play concerns
about privacy. Now privacy is a big legal
area. It's developing very quickly. There
are lots of questions about privacy online
in various kinds of digital context which
are still not fully addressed by these
existing legal system. It's also something
that varies tremendously based on where
you are. Here in the United States where
I'm based, we tend to have a fairly less
on fair attitude toward privacy. We let
companies do a great deal without
prospective regulation in Europe and oth
er part s of the world there tends to be
much stricter constraints on what can be
done with private information, what sorts
of data collected and what can be done
with it. So be careful when designing a
gamified system especially any time you
are getting access to personal
identifiable information. Information that
tells you something definitely about a
single individual. Second issue flows from
the discussion earlier about exploitation
and playbore. The concern that a gamified
system could give rise to employment or
labor law issues. So I put up here the
graphic from the target checkout system
that tells people their score. And I
talked about the potential for that to
feel manipulative to the workers. I also
gave you the example of the so called
electronic whip at the Disneyland Hotels.
That one in fact, came out of a labor
dispute where the workers were complaining
about their working conditions and one of
the issues that they brought up was this
leaderboard system. So, there are a
variety of rules in many countries
restricting what you can do as an employer
vis-a-vis your employees and there are
also are rules when employees get together
and want to collectively bargain. As with
many other aspects of law, they vary
country to country and employment law
restrictions tend to be far stricter in
European countries than they are in the
United States but even in the United
States there are limitations and
considerations on which you can do. So
these are issues that will come up in any
kind of internal gamification situation
where the game elements are being used in
some way that effects peoples work
performance. And the question is whether
it's being properly disclosed. And whether
it's consistent with what the law requires
as far as working conditions. Next issue
is the potential for deceptive marketing.
And so I gave you early in the course the
Jesse Schell video from Dice where he
talked about the potential of gamification
somewhat joking or sarcastically. And he
spun out these scenarios where gaming and
game elements w ere embedded as
advertising everywhere in the world and in
fact even piped directly into your brain
through some advertising mechanism. A lot
of those ideas if they became reality,
would give us pause. And there are rules
even when you don't go that far about what
you can do to market something. And in
particular, some of these concerns have to
do with stealth marketing. If the gamified
system is not clearly designed to market.
If people think that they're just playing
a game for fun, but in fact, this is
designed to get them to buy a product.
There might be a concern that that's some,
somehow a deceptive trade practice. Things
like advertising in particular are
regulated in some countries. So there's a
broad area there for external marketing
focus gamification where there might be
issues if it's not clear to the people
involved, that this is a marketing
technique. If it's clear, if people
understand that this is like advertising
or something else that's trying to sell
them something, then it's not necessarily
problematic. But the fact that the games
make people feel like something is
rewarding for some reason other than the
product they're getting, opens the door to
this being a problem. The next one is
intellectual property. This is a huge
issue across the board on all sorts of
digital technologies and digital
activities. Intellectual property law
regulates access to information or digital
assets. And so all of the virtual goods in
a gamified system, even things like the
badges, the visual aspects of the system
are potentially protected by intellectual
property law. And, this is an issue with
again, any kind of digital system. But
it's possible in designing a gamified
system, if you think that things like the
structure and the badges are something
that you can take from someone else's
system, you might run into problems in
that area. Beyond intellectual property
generally is the question about virtual
goods and virtual assets. And wheth er
they may have some legally protected value
above and beyond what they m ean in terms
of intellectual property. So this is an
issue that's come up with online games.
What happens if a user spends a tremendous
amount of time and effort and maybe even
pays real money to get something virtual
in the game. In the game what they get is
this beautiful building here, do they have
something of value? What happens if the
game designer wants to take it away. Poof.
It's gone. Or somehow change the rules and
the value. Does the person who acquired
that thing, again at great cost of time
and potentially cost of real money have
any legal claim as they would have for
example if someone sold them some physical
product and then tried to take it away in
an analogous situation. The courts so far
have said not really, the courts so far
have said this is a license. It's
something you get contractually but not
something you get as a property right. But
this is an emerging and evolving area of
the law, and one to keep an eye on in
things like gamification. There are also
are some specific issues with virtual
currencies. There's a law in the US called
the card act here which regulates gift
cards which are similar in some ways to
some of these gamified virtual assets or
virtual currencies. In that, you are
paying real money to get the gift card,
which then is a kind of virtual token that
you can redeem at the store. And so issues
come up like what if the gift card
expires? Someone paid money for it, but
can the company then say great, we just
keep the money and don't have to give you
anything. There's potential for abuse
there, so that law regulates the use of
stored value in this way on cards. Not
clear how it applies in gamification, and
again here we're talking about
specifically things like virtual
currencies. Not badges and leaderboards
and so forth that, that don't have some
tangible value somehow attached to them.
But in that area there are some questions
that can be raised abo ut the legal
treatment of these kinds of services. So
all of these are issues to keep an eye out
for, depending on the nature of the
gamified system that you're developing.
There are of course, many other legal
issues that will come into play. Just like
any kind of business activity. But when in
doubt, probably a good idea to consult
with counsel or someone has some more
expertise about the legal issues
especially as they apply in the particular
jurisdiction that you're in.