There are many mistakes that you can make
in designing a gamified system. But, one
of the most common and one of the most
dangerous is to forget about who the
object at the system is, namely, the
players. And to forget that players are
people, they're human beings. They're
thinking, and feeling, and interacting
agents. And while you can anticipate in
many ways how their going to behave, and
certainly anticipate the different kinds
of motivational structures that might push
them in one direction or another, you can
never be sure what their going to do. And,
in designing gamified systems, it's
critical to recognize that one thing that
players may do is game the system. They
may turn the tables on you and do
something that you never expected and
never intended. Sometimes this can be
dangerous not just for you, but for them.
Nicole Lazzaro, the game designer who
developed the concept of four types of
fun, gives a great example in her
presentations, which she calls,
Gamification Can Kill. And the example is
the on ramp to the San Francisco Bay
bridge, maybe it's the Golden Gate bridge.
But, it's one of the bridges in San
Francisco, California. And like many urban
transit systems, they have a system for
pricing that's congestion based. The price
goes up during rush hour to try to
encourage people to go across the bridge
at less busy times. So you see here at
six:59, I think this must be PM it's six
bucks to go over the bridge but it's
seven, a minute later it's only four bucks
to go over the bridge. Great, incentive
systems, you call it a gamified system,
you can call it behavioral economics. It
suddenly encourages people to drive during
off hours. What's the problem? The problem
as points out, is if you drive towards the
bridge at six:59 p.m., you will see a
whole bunch of people swerving off the
road. Trying to park on the side because
they know that if they wait just a minute
or two more to go over the bridge it's
$two less. And the problem is what this is
incentivizing people to do is to swerve
dangerously off t h e road in ways that
might cause them to get in an accident.
And so that's the point about gamification
can kill. We have to realize how people
are going to respond to do these systems.
They may very well react to the prompts
that are given not necessarily in the ways
that are anticipated or even too much in
the way that they, that are, the ways that
are anticipated and that could be
dangerous. Now, one dimension of this is a
recognition that sometimes people will
cheat. That sometimes people will figure
out a way to achieve their own aims in the
system that are not the aims of the game
designer. Maybe there's some flaw in the
game that lets people accumulate vast
numbers of points for a small amount of
work. And if that option is there, many
people will take it. Now, as I talked
about, part of what makes a game a game is
that the players have to voluntarily
accept the rules of the game. That often,
there are opportunities to cheat in the
game but we don't do them, because if we
do, then we're not following the rules,
we're not playing the game, we're just
doing something else entirely. And the
people around us, our opponent, the other
participants, won't even recognize that
we're playing the game. But in gamified
systems, where we're dealing with people
interacting with computer based software
systems. Often even though they're in a
social context, they're interacting
individually, it's often easy for people
to feel like the game that they are
playing is one that allows them to. Bend
the rules or make their own rules in ways
that the game designer would consider
cheating. Interestingly enough well
designed games that have social elements
tend to see this last because the social
pressure, whether explicit or implicit, is
enough to get people not to cheat even in
ways that they could. But even there,
there is the potential if the rewards are
great enough or the incentive is great
enough that people may try to tackle
corners. And this is something that
depending on the nature of the sys tem
maybe the game designer will just live
with, or maybe it's something that the
game needs to be expressly built with the
anticipation that people act that way.
This is a big reason why iteration and
play testing is so critical in designing
games as well as in effective gamification
design because you can never be sure what
exactly people are going to do until you
get them in and see them actually doing
it. In some cases though, cheating may be
a virtue. It may actually help achieve the
results that the game designer is thinking
about. How can that be? Well, let me give
you one example. James Gardner is an
innovation designer who now works for a
company called Spigot that makes a
gamified prediction market system that can
be used in companies to develop
innovations by creating contests where
people bet real money or virtual goods
that potentially are translatable to real
money on new ideas. And, he's been part of
teams that have developed these kinds of
systems in many different context,
originally in England. He famously
developed the idea street program at the
Department of Welfare and Pensions in the
UK. But before that, he did it for Loyd's
Bank. And something interesting happened
at Loyd's Bank where they created the
innovation market. So, this was a market
place where you came up with ideas that
would be helpful innovations for the bank
and people could buy and sell those
innovations. And people could get together
in teams to develop the innovations and
the market we determine which were the
more popular and more successful ones and
then the company would take the more
successful ones and try and implement
them. And they found in this a lot of
cases, lots of amazing results in
implementing the ideas that bubble to the
top through this production market place.
But something interesting happened at
Loyd's when they applied this Gamified
System Insider Trading. People realized
that they could find the good ideas and go
and join up with those groups and be able
to buy and sell with th e ideas that were
rising and successful in the syst 'em. In
financial markets, insider trading is a
danger, it's cheating. It's a form of
fraud because it's using information that
you have that other people don't have. It
undermines trust in the financial markets,
that's a reason that it's often
prosecuted. But in this gamified system,
this kinda virtual insider trading was not
a bug but actually a feature. Because it
was a way of strengthening and growing the
teams around the great ideas. And it was a
way of reinforcing, providing additional
signal value around the ideas that people
thought had great potential which is what
the game applied system was about. It was
not about making money for people or
making money for companies that were
issuing securities, it was about finding
and developing great ideas and reinforcing
them. So, the gaming of the game by the
participants as Gardner realized was
actually something that helped achieve
that result. In all of these cases again,
the critical piece is to recognize that
people will act in unpredictable,
sometimes spontaneous ways in response to
the signals that the system produces. And
so part of game design is building in
structures that first of all, ensure that
those activities, if there aren't
anticipated, don't destroy the game. Don't
create imbalances or otherwise make the
game unplayable or undesirable for a large
segment of the players. And ideally,
create systems so that they help the game.
So that even though people aren't doing
what the game designer expressly told them
to, they're exercising their autonomy and
therefore, feeling more intrinsically
motivated in the activity and doing things
that get to the same result that the
gamification system was originally
designed to accomplish.