One criticism of gamification is that it's
ineffective, because it only uses the
surface mechanics and other elements from
games and thus, should really be called
pointification. A second criticism is that
gamification is potentially too effective,
that it can be used to get people to do
things that aren't necessarily in their
interest. And that criticism goes by the
name of exploitationware. I've already
shown you some examples in this vein when
talking about enterprise gamification and
the concept of play board or coerced play.
For example, the leader board for the
housekeeping staff at some of the
Disneyland hotels, where the employees
felt like the gamefication techniques were
not encouraging and motivating them. In
fact, they were controlling and
manipulating them and forcing them to
compete more aggressively just to keep up.
That's an example of gamefication being
used in a way that potentially is
exploitative as opposed to encouraging and
supportive of the employees. The term
exploitationware was coined by Ian Bogost,
who's a noted game designer and researcher
at Georgia Tech University, in a post that
appeared on his personal blog and also on
the games industry blog Gamasutra. Here's
the URL to the personal blog version of
it. And, he essentially made two
arguments. One was that gamification if,
people like, like Margaret Robertson say,
it's an inadvertent con, it's accidentally
misleading people about the nature of
games. Bogost says, no, actually, it's an
intentional con. Gamification is a way to
try to make people think that their job
doesn't suck, even when it does. So,
gamefication, he says, is inherently a
technique that can be used as a way to
confuse people and to make them ignore the
real conditions of their workplace as
opposed to focusing on the actual
compensation and meaningfulness and
rewarding aspects of the job. The broader
point though that Bogost makes in calling
gamification exploitationware is that it
fundamentally undermines the nature of
economic and social exchange between w
orkers and their employers. And his
argument goes like this. He says,
gamification proposes to replace real
incentives with fictional ones. So, in
other words, if the idea is we can
motivate people with shiny badges and
points, and all of these virtual
techniques that lead to no tangible
material rewards, then companies will
start to do that instead of rewarding and
incentivizing their employees with things
like money, or better working conditions,
or more job responsibility. And his
argument is that essentially, this
undermines the bargain between both sides,
because the workers are still giving up
their effort and their productivity, but
what they're getting in return is
something that is ultimately empty. Maybe
for a little bit, they feel like it's
something motivating, but really what the
company is doing is again, an intentional
con, is saying, instead of giving you
something that we know is valuable to you
and which is costly to us to give, we're
going to give you something that we think
of as virtually free to basically trick
you into thinking that you're getting a
reward that's meaningful. And so, that's
the argument about exploitationware and
it's one that is worth taking into
account. Bogost does have a point and, in
fact, there are examples we can see,
including some of the ones that I've given
you in the course, where gamification is
not necessarily something that's done to
make workers better off. But here, as with
many other examples of gamification, the
real question is how are the tools being
used? The same context can be used in
exploitative ways or in ways that are
healthy for workers. For example, in the
call center space, there are examples of
gamification that are about manipulation,
that are about companies wanting to track,
ever more closely, what workers are doing
in order to manage them in ways that don't
help the workers at all. They treat them
as commodities and that probably are not
ultimately healthy for the companies
themselves because they're so short term
focused. And at the same time, there are
examples in the call center world of
gamification systems that encourage people
as call center operators, to learn and to
feel more engagement and more meaning in
their work. So, the problem I think, is
not gamification, per se, the problem is
use of gamification, either inadvertently
without an awareness that there can be a
divergence between the players interest
and at least a short term version of the
system designers interest. Or deliberately
as a trick, as a shortcut to force people
to do something. This is something that's
dangerous, that's harmful. And that
gamification designers need to be careful
to avoid. But it's something that can
happen easily if you're not careful.
Bogost, himself designed a wonderful proof
of the ease of reaching this conclusion
with something he created called Cow
Clicker. And Cow Clicker was something
that Bogost created on a lark. It was
partly a way to make fun of social games
like the Zinga games, that are so driven
by virtual goods and virtual currency, and
these appointment dynamics of trying to
get people to feel like they're crops are
going to rot so they have to come back
right away. And so, what Bogost did was
created something like one of these social
games called Cow Clicker, that had no
point whatsoever. The mechanic of the
games was, you have to click on a cow.
That's it. You click on the cow, you click
on the cow again, you click on the cow
again. But, there are all different kinds
of cows. The cows are virtual goods. So,
there are some cows that are more rare.
There are some cows that you unlock by
clicking a lot, or clicking at certain
times. And the game is designed to show at
least to Bogost, the fundamental emptiness
of these kinds of systems that rely purely
on these engagement loops. And it turns
out what happened was 50,000 plus people
started playing this game, which again,
had no point whatsoever other than to show
how silly this idea was. People were
actually doing it, people were clicking o
n the cows time and time and time again.
And ultimate ly there were people topping
the leaderboard with vasts amounts of the
games virtual currency which could only be
accumulated if they had clicked hundreds
of thousands of times on these cows. So,
clearly, people do surprising things.
Things that, may at first glance, makes no
sense, if they are drawn in by these kinds
of habit forming engagement based system.
That's part of what can make them useful,
but it is also what makes them dangerous.
So, in designing gamification, the first
step in the process, the first step in the
gamification design framework that I gave
you, is to focus on the business
objectives. What's the purpose here?
What's the purpose of encouraging people
to take some action? How does it really
tie to a deep important business or other
goal? And the second thing is who are the
players. It's critical to focus on the
people who were involved in the game and
not to treat them just as automatons that
are forced or suckered into participating
this, in this activity, which doesn't
really benefit them. So, exploitation are
like pointsification is a legitimate
criticism, is one that's successful and
thoughtful gamification designers need to
take into account and is one that should
be part of your thinking whenever you try
to understand how to apply these
techniques that I've talked about to a
problem that you've defined.