The promise of gamification is to learn
from games, to draw on what makes games so
powerful and apply it in other contexts.
So it's a fair question to ask whether
gamification can or in fact does actually
accomplish that? And there are many who
argue that it doesn't. This criticism goes
by the name of pointsification. A term
that was coined by Margaret Robertson. A
British game developer in her blog Hide
and Seek. And in her original post back in
2010, what she argued and what many other
had since developed in other ways is that
gamification is about taking the things
that is least essential from games and
representing it as the core of the
experience. In other words gamification
relies just on the surface aspects of
games. The mechanics. The other game
elements. And what she says is that's not
the important stuff. That's not the part
of games that makes them wonderful. That
gets people to play and that stimulates
that powerful set of motivational aspects
that we've talked about in the course. So
what she says is, as she goes on in the
post, effectively gamification is an
inadvertent con. It's genuine. It's trying
to take something valuable from games but
it's taking the wrong thing. And in so
doing it's inadvertently misleading
people. It's suggesting to people that
what's great about games is that they have
things like point systems and
leaderboards. When in fact that's not
what's central or important about games at
all. And there's a great deal of bite to
this criticism. As we've talked about many
gamified system rely principally on
points, badges, leaderboards and a few
other surface level game mechanics. And,
well may that have some valuable fact that
we can link them to other sorts of
activities like loyalty programs. They
don't necessarily produce the sense of
true engagement and the sense of intrinsic
motivation, that's so important to really
changeing behavior and really producing
sustained results in ways that are
beneficial for people involved in the
system. So there is a legitimate criticism
here aro und pointsification. But to my
mind it's one that can be addressed by
thinking about gamification more broadly.
As I've talked about, there really are two
streams of work that feed into
gamification. The one that Robertson and
the other critics are talking about when
they label it pointsification is entirely
on the behavioral side. And it's the
shallower aspects of applying those
behavioral techniques through
gamification. Again, predominately using
simple mechanics like points and leader
boards, and thinking that they can just be
slapped onto processes and produce
results. I would certainly agree that
that's limiting, and that, that doesn't
produce the same kinds of powerful results
that we can see from games, but...
Gamification at least appropriately
thought of is much more than that. So part
of the criticism of pointification is
focusing in on a limited set but a very
real set of gamification examples and
practises. And I think that we can take it
to heart without necessarily writing off
the entire practice of gamification. But
an important question this raises is
whether gamification really is effective.
Robertson as a game designer was concerned
about gamification having the effect of
belittling games. That if people started
to think, "Oh wait. Games are just about
points and badges and stuff like that."
And those really aren't that effective. So
therefore games must not be that
interesting or powerful, either. As a game
designer, that was her concern. She wasn't
particularly concerned about gamification
as a practice. But those of us who are in
the gamification field certainly are. And
so it's worth asking whether if
gamification reduces to pointsification,
then that means that it won't produce the
kind of sustained, important, deep
engagement that's necessary to drive real
business results and real behavior change.
And the challenge here is we don't have a
tremendous amount of research. In this
course, I have given you many different
examples, some anecdotal, some involving
data points. But we do n't hav e yet
significant empirical research,
systematically looking at different forms
of gamification and the results that it
can provide in the enterprise, in external
marketing context, in behavior change
context. There are social scientists,
people like my colleague, Ethan Mollick,
here at the Wharton School, who started to
do research in this area. And I think that
we'll see research start to come about
that informs gamification practice. But up
to this point, it's limited. I think
there's enough examples. Again, we've seen
many of them in this course that suggest
that these techniques are valid, and can
work if designed and applied
appropriately. But we don't yet know as
much as we need to about what the data
really show in large scale practical
deployments. The second issue that this
comes to is that gamification if it does
reduce to pointsification, if most of the
time or at least some of the time it turns
out to just be about using these shallow
elements. There's a very real risk that
engagement may spike initially but will
then decay. That people may feel that
initial boost from the surprise or the
activity and engagement loops of feedback.
But ultimately if they're just driven by
those behaviourist rewards or just driven
by the surface level mechanics they'll get
bored. And that won't produce an induring
response. That's I think a fair criticism
and something to be aware of in designing
gamified systems. And yet another reason.
Not to just stop by thinking about these
simple points based mechanics. The third
aspect of this is one that we've already
talked about, which is the potential for
crowding out, or over justification. So,
if in fact gamification becomes just
pointsification, then it falls victim to
all the dangers of extrinsic rewards that
I described in some of the psychology
sections. All of this together is what is
like Kathy Sierra, who is a noted author
and speaker around interaction design and
programming in other areas. She has been a
frequent critic of gamifica tion and has
labeled it, I think very powerfully as the
high fructose corn syrup of engagement and
what I think she's saying there is first
of all that it takes the richness, the
real organic value of games and of human
engagement, and reduces it down to
something very simplistic and very shrill.
And that it's something like corn syrup
high fructose corn syrup that seems great
because it's sweet and cheap. But that as
we learn more turns out to potentially be
harmful for us. In the sense here, that if
we rely too much on these simplistic,
external reward based systems, that it
will push people away from the true
intrinsic motivation. Love of the
activity, love of the task, love of the
process. That is what should ultimately be
driving them. And as with the
pointsification critic more broadly, this
is something worth taking into account.
Now, again I tend to think that its not a
fatal critic of all of gamification for
the reason that are described in the
course but its something that you should
always have in mind when designing
systems. And always try to think about how
avoid sliding down that path where infact
what you are doing is not gamafiying, but
just applying point systems or applying
game mechanics and other game elements in
situations where they are not truely
appropriate. So, let's turn back to the
Foursquare example. Foursquare, in many
ways, was a tremendous success story for
gamification. The use of game elements,
the badges, the points and so forth, on
top of the social location system that was
pioneered by Dodgeball, helped power
Foursquare to tremendous success and
tremendous adoption. But along the way
something interesting happened. Early in
2012 Foursquare did a redesign. They
changed the interface of the system in a
way that appeared to significantly
de-emphasize the game elements. So here
you see some screen shots of the
Foursquare iPhone client. And you see
here's one main screen that shows
information about your friends and where
they are and information that yo u can
post. And you notice. Not a lot of game
elements actu ally there. And here's the
screen showing your friends, where they've
checked in on the map. Again, the game
elements aren't that prominent. It's only
when you get to this third screen here
that we see. The stats with the crown we
see the badges that you've accomplished,
that you've achieved and so forth. So the
game elements are still there, but they
appear to much less prominent. So the
question is what lesson to draw from this
and I think one can draw a couple of
different lessons. One conclusion is..
Gamification didn't work. The game
elements either didn't actually produce
business results or maybe they did for
awhile but then people got bored. People
got tired of them. The badges just became
something silly and not something that
really motivated people to want to check
in and participate in the service. Or
maybe another conclusion one could draw is
that the game elements are still there.
And still important to the service. But it
was much more important to make them
prominent during the early days when
Foursquare was trying to grow, trying to
get out of that trap that I described
early on, where there was no reason for
people to check in if their friends were
checking in. And there were no real
super-users who had a motivation to go and
check in all the time at certain location
and post information. So perhaps the game
elements were particularly important
during that growth phase for the company.
And now that it reached the critical mass,
where the key is monetization and building
out off of the large number of users to
real rich informational and social value
that people can extract out, and that gets
people to put more deep information into
the system. Maybe at that point. The
point, badge and leader board type game
elements are less central. So you can
decide whichever of those stories you
think persuades you or maybe some other
story. But again, in thinking about
gamefication in practice , it behooves
everyone to try to keep questionin g
whether this is a technique that's worth
using. I think it's one that can be
extremely valuable in many different
areas. Going from very lightweight systems
to much more sophisticated deployments.
But it's, again, not something that's
useful for everyone, and not something
that's useful in every single case. So,
what are some implications to take away
from this discussion? First, names are
powerful. Much of the fire behind the
criticism of gamification from game
designers hinges on the word,
gamification. Because it implies that this
is about games. And I think, if you think
about it broadly as I have talked about,
it is. It involves using many different
aspects of games and many different
aspects of game design practice. But it is
true that if gamification is just pulling
out points at the few other mechanics,
then it is something substantially less.
Than the full panoply of richness that
games entail. So names matter. The problem
is names are names, and gamification is
the name that has stuck. Maybe eventually
it will go away or change into something
else, but for now it's the word that gets
used for this practice. Second point is,
bad de-gamification is bad. So it's true
that if gamification just uses points,
badges, and leader boards, especially if
it does it in a very shallow way, and
certainly there are many examples of that
today, that it's going to be limited. It's
not going to produce sustained engagement,
and it may, in fact, be harmful. It may,
in fact, produce the kind of backlash, the
crowding out effect that we described in
the discussion of behaviorism and
psychology. Third point is that there's
more to games than gamification. So games
do involve many other aspects beyond the
ones that we've talked about in this
class. And there's more to gamification
than games. Gamification draws upon areas
like phsychology and design and business
practice and social media in many ways
that go beyond or go in different
directions than game design and that's
fine. That's one reason it's important t o
keep straight whether we're talking about
games including for example serio us game
design. Or talking about gamification
where the goal is to apply to some
non-game context. And, final lesson here.
Caveat Ludor, let the gamifier beware.
Make sure to always keep in mind. The
difference between gamification and
pointsification and to recognize the bite
that, that criticism has.