In addition to the legal considerations
about gamification, there are a series of
what we might call regulatory concerns.
Areas where some practice might be allowed
but it's subject to various restrictions
by administrative and other agencies. So,
let me go through a few of these quickly.
Most of them like the legal issues become
particularly serious when there's money
involved. The first though, doesn't
necessarily require that. It's the
situation where someone is surreptitiously
becoming a marketer or an endorser for a
product. The Federal Trade Commision in
the United States promulgated a set of
rules in the past few years that were
primarily targeted at bloggers who were
being given money or free products or
other consideration by companies in order
to write wonderful things about those
companies on their blogs. Some of them
were people who actually liked the
products and just appreciated getting free
stuff. But in some cases, the people were
effectively becoming paid endorsers. And
yet, to the readers of the blog, they were
just some person who was writing an
individual blog, and happened to genuinely
love these products. So, the Federal Trade
Commission issued rules, essentially
requiring disclosure saying, that if you
are endorsing a product in some public way
because they gave you something, then you
have to disclose that fact and not have
people think that you're endorsing the
product purely because you happen to love
it. So, how does this connect with
gamification? Well, one of the ways that
many gamefication systems in marketing
provide opportunities for people to get
points, is by recommending products or
companies through social media. So, for
example, here, this is the Samsung Nation
service, which I've used a number of times
before. And one of the badges it has is a
badge that you can unlock here by liking
this post. So if you like the post about
Samsung Nation then you unlock a badge.
And there are other badges and
achievements in this and other
gamification systems that involve t hings
like twee ting about a company or a
product, liking it on Facebook, or posting
something on it on Facebook or elsewhere.
And these are situations that might give
rise to this requirement of disclosure.
Now, in these cases, the person involved
is not necessarily getting paid directly.
They're just getting some virtual value
through the point system or the
achievements in the gamified system, which
itself may or may not produce tangible
real rewards. But it's worth thinking
about if this is a key structure in the
gamified system whether, at some point, it
might run afoul of some of these rules.
Second concern from the standpoint of
regulation is banking. If in fact, what's
involved in the gamified system is a
currency, is something that is like money
or that is freely tradable back and forth
with money, then potentially all of the
kinds of requirements that apply to banks,
things like record keeping, reserve
requirements, things about currency
manipulation, fraud, money laundering is a
big one, restrictions on taking money in
and out of countries, consumer protection
laws, taxation rules, accounting rules.
All that stuff potentially applies or
maybe, you, as the service provider are
not permitted to engage in this activity
unless you are registered and regulated as
a bank. So, this is something that
typically a gamified system provider or a
company that's using some sort of gamified
system, is not going to want to have to
deal with. They're not in this because
they want to build a full-fledge financial
institution even if they're using some
sort of virtual goods or virtual
currency-type system as part of their
platform. Again, this is something that
you're probably not going to run into with
most gamified systems, but worth keeping
in mind if there is real money going in or
out of the system and there is some
tradable structure around a virtual
currency. The third one is gambling and
sweepstakes. So, again, if there's some
reward, some valuable tangible reward that
can be achieved thro ugh the system then,
there is the pote ntial to get swept up
under either sweepstakes laws which, at
least in the United States, are
predominantly issues at the state level,
where different states have different
requirements about what kinds of
sweepstakes you can do, whether, for
example, you have to require that someone
be able to enter the sweepstakes without
having bought your product and so forth,
that's one category. If the idea is
basically, this is a random drawing in
return for buying a ticket, participating
by using a product or something else, that
you're going to win some money if you're
the winner of the sweepstakes. Then
potentially, if the gamified system has
some structure that looks like that, you
have to think about those rules. Or, on
the other hand, if this is considered
gambling, then a whole other set of rules
apply, and these are predominantly at the
national level. So, in the United States,
interstate gambling, is by and large
prohibited. What is permitted is gambling
in designated areas, like Las Vegas and
Atlantic City, and on certain Indian
reservations, and government sponsored
lotteries, as well as a variety of other
things that are not quite considered
gambling. In many other countries,
gambling is permitted, but regulated for
access to children and so forth. And we
have all kinds of questions that come up
when online gambling sites locate outside
of the United States or in other places
and then they're available to people in
different countries. The point here is
that if a gamified system seems like
gambling, I've already talked about a few
times the slot machine-like aspect of some
gamified systems and the fact that these
are systems that can actually tie into
real tangible rewards. If what this looks
like is a different way of gambling, then
potentially regulators will say, it's
subject to those gaming rules and maybe
even those prohibitions if it is in
country like the United States that has
regulations on gambling. So, this is again
something to think abo ut where there is
money involved. There is a distinction in
g ambling law between what are called,
games of skill and games of chance. The
idea being that basically gambling is all
over here, gambling is something where
essentially, you're not guaranteed that
you're going to win based on your skill,
you're just hoping to win based on, say, a
pull of the lever on a slot machine. On
the other hand, if it's primarily about
skill, if you're winning a prize for doing
something effectively whether that's
winning a prize for winning a sports
contest or for winning some other kind of
contest, where the most skillful person is
the winner, then, the gambling laws don't
necessarily apply in the same way. And the
question is in a gamified system where
there might be elements of randomness and
also elements of skill involved, which
side of the line would it fall under?
Again, if anything like this is
potentially an issue with the system that
you're involved with a good idea to call
in someone with more specific legal
knowledge to think about it and help
advise you on what to do. Now, these are,
by no means, all of the legal and
regulatory questions that might come up
with regard to gamification. But they're
some of the bigger ones that might lead to
a particularly serious problem if the
system covers the area that the legal or
regulatory restriction involves and it's
not done in a way that takes into account
what those obligations might entail.