In this unit I'm going to talk about
designing using game elements. Now that
you've oriented yourself to think like a
game designer, how do you practically take
things out of games and apply them to
business practices. As I mentioned in the
introductory unit, game elements are your
toolbox for gamification. So think about
it, if you're trying to build a house, you
wouldn't go out to the hardware store and
ask to buy a house gun, that somehow shot
out completely formed houses. No, what you
do is you buy things like hammers, and
nails, and screwdrivers. And two by 4's
and Sheep Rock. All the different
components that you can put together in
different ways to make up a house. To make
up any kind of house or any kind of
building that you want by recombining
those elements in different ways. So
that's what we mean when we talk about
game elements. They are regular patterns.
They are tools that we can extract from
games that we find in the wild and then
use in different ways to make business
practices more game-like. So you'll recall
I gave the example earlier on of Empires
and Allies, the Zynga game, or I showed
you the game and then showed you some of
the different kinds of elements. Things
like the points and the quests and the
levels and so forth. This is a template
for what games elements might look like
but let's step back and talk about what
game elements are initially. And then
we'll build up a list of common game
elements that are used in gamification. So
let me draw for you here something that
will probably be familiar to most of you.
Starting to look familiar? How about this?
Okay. By now. You probably are recognizing
that what I've drawn is the game
Tic-Tac-Toe or in the commonwealth world
it's known as Knots and Crosses. One Of
the most popular games of all time played
for many centuries. It's a game many of us
are familiar with but what if you think
about this game Tic-tac-toe not through
the lens of the game itself. Not through
the lens of the game play. Here I am
playing. Ahah, I've forked and now this
guy's going to win but think about it
through the lens of elements. What are the
elements of Tic-tac-toe? What are the
regular paterns? The pieces of this game
that come together along with the
aesthetics and the overall experience to
generate the game play. Stop and see if
you can think about some of the different
elements that we make up the game call
Tic-tac-toe. There's no one universal list
but you can probably come up with some of
them that are fairly easy to spot. Here's
a list of elements in Tic-tac-toe that I
made. There is of course the game board
that pattern of lines that create nine
spots that you can play in and there are
the tokens as I call them, the X and the O
that you play with. There are also, there
is also the fact that Tic-Tac-Toe is a
game played with two players. Now, that's
not anywhere there on the board. It's part
of the rules of the game and it's part of
the structures of the game. The rules are
things like you play an X and then the
next player plays an O. You can only play
in one square and so forth. I'm talking
about things that structure the game that
go to the essence of what makes it
engaging or not. So one of them is
Tic-tac-toe is a game played between two
players who are competitive i.e one person
wins, one person looses. It's not a bunch
of people who are collaborating to find a
solution. It's one winner and one loser in
every game or the games a draw. They take
turns, that's part of the structure of the
game. That one player goes and then the
other player goes and the game defines
certain situations where we say one player
wins. So, if in fact, I'm able to make
three x's in a row here. I have won the
game. That is called a win state.
Similarly if we get to a point where all
the boxes are filled up, and no one has
three in a row, that's a draw. And if you
saw the movie War Games, the computer
figured out somehow in its vast
intelligence that any two decently
competent Tic-tac-toe players can generate
a draw in every single game, no way to win
the gam E. Now, in that movie, that result
almost lead to nuclear war. We don't have
to worry about that but the point that I
want to make here. Is that the structure
of the game. The elements of what it takes
to win and what it takes to draw the game.
Contributes to. The gameplay. And
contributes to the way people feel in
playing Tic-Tac-Toe. How much fun it is.
How much people want to keep playing. How
interesting it seems and so forth. And all
of this feeds in to gamification. We start
to think about deploying these tools
systematically. There's no, one set of
elements that's always good or always bad.
They have to be understood in context of
the overall game. So a few other, there's,
there's no progression. Now this is a
limitation on Tic-tac-toe. It doesn't
necessarily get better or change. As you
play. There's no level one Tic-tac-toe and
then once you finish this board here you
go on to level two. Nor is there any kind
of scoring less you just keep track of who
wins each game. It's just you play the
game and you win or you lose. These are
also elements about why when you think
about it, Tic-tac-toe is a pretty bad
game. Incredibly popular for centuries of
human history and yet a game that is so
simplistic and so easy to draw that it's
not going to hold any adult's interest for
very long. And again you can see that from
the elements that are there and some of
the elements that are missing. The ability
to progress and advance in a game and the
ability to get feedback from scoring.
Certainly not necessary as I've said but
things that tend to produce more engaging
games than games without them. So another
way to think about this is, if we talk
about a game here in the middle. And we
can think about that through the various
definitions that I gave you. At the top is
the experience. The overall impact of the
game, what you feel like when you play the
game, that's the experience. First point
here is that. This here, the game and this
here the experience are not the same
thing. The game is the set of rules, the a
esthetics, all of the game elements. The
experience is what the player feels when
they're playing it. Those two are very
much related but they're different things
and when you're doing game design what you
control is the game and what you try to
produce is a certain kind of experience.
The other side to this is what's down here
which are the elements. So if the
experience is the kind of gestalt, the
overall impact or feeling of the game, the
elements are the piece parts. The bits and
pieces if you build up the game from
smaller units. Than you're building up
from elements if you think about the game
in terms of its general impact. How fun it
feels and why it feels fun. You're talking
about the experience. And really both of
these are ways to think about
gamification. We're going to focus mostly
on going up from the elements but
gamification is also about. Again,
thinking like a game designer and trying
to understand how overall experiences that
we can understand from games. Can be put
into non-game context using things like
elements but also using other kinds of