As we saw when examining Tic-Tac-Toe, or
you prefer Noughts and Crosses, there are
many different game elements. And if you
look at all of the games that you can
think of, you'd find a vast array of
different things you may consider as
elements, as templates or design patterns
that can be applied in other games or in
gamification. But when we examine
prominent examples of gamification.
Including the ones that we've covered in
this class for the most part. Certain
elements recur again and again. And most
of them are derived directly from, social
games online or from other kinds of online
video games. So I've developed a framework
for, gamification elements. These are the
common elements that are found in
gamification, and some structure around
the different kinds of those elements.
These are not every possible element. Nor
are these the best elements. Nor are these
elements that should be in every example
of gamification. Again the best example is
not the one that uses the most elements
it's the one that uses the elements the
most effectively. But this framework
should give you some sense of how the
different kinds of elements or pieces from
games can be applied in different ways and
it's a pyramid structure that has three
levels. The three levels being the
dynamics on top. The mechanics in the
middle and the components on the bottom.
And I'll describe each of those in some
detail. The one point to make though
before I go on is that this is not the
totality. Again this is just the elements.
And around the elements is the overall
experience of the game. It's the aspect of
the game that's not captured fully by the
elements. It's the whole that's greater
than the sum of the parts. And, a critical
part of that experience is the aesthetics
of the game. The visual experience of the
game. The, sound. The other aspects that
tie the game together and make it feel
somehow real to the players. All of that
is above and beyond the elements, all of
that is certainly extremely important in
games and often important in g amifica
tion, but that's the part you have to
design creatively based on the
circumstances. What we're going to focus
on here is the generic patterns, the
aspects that can be taken from games and
applied to generate specific kinds of
results. And one point to add before I go
into more detail. You may recall Marc
LeBlanc the game designer who developed
the notion of Eight kinds of Fun that I
mentioned in an earlier segment. He also
created an influential framework for
understanding all games called the MDA
Framework. And MDA stands for Mechanics
Dynamics Aesthetics. So it sounds very
much like the framework for gamification
elements I just gave you. There are some
simularities although LeBlanc uses those
terms in somewhat different ways. Much of
what he calls aesthetics is what we talk
about under the rubric of fun. But
LeBlanc's framework has been as they said
very influential in helping designers and
theorists conceptualise different aspects
of games and how to create them, so if
your interested in finding out more.
Here's a link to a paper that he
co-authored that goes into detail on the
MDA framework. So now back to the pyramid
of game elements. At the top of the
pyramid are the game dynamics. These are
the most high level conceptual elements.
In a game or a gamified system. I like to
think of them as the grammar. The hidden
structure that, makes the experience
somehow cohere and have regular patterns.
They're not. The same thing as the rules.
The rules are specific to any game. The
rules in Tic-Tac-Toe are you put your x
and they put their o and there is a
certain place that you can put them, and
so on and so forth. The dynamics are the
implicit structure which the rules, maybe
a surface manifestation of... But they
also include more conceptual kinds of
elements that provide the framing for the
game. So, for example, constraints, every
game has some constraints. Because game
create meaningful choices and interesting
problems by limiting people's freedom, so
the notion of what constraints can put on
users is a n impo rtant dynamic that any
game designer needs to think about.
Emotions. Games can produce almost any
emotion you can think of, from joy to
sadness to everything in between. The
emotional palette of gamification is
typically somewhat more limited, because
we are dealing with real world, non game
context, whether those are at work or a
marketing context or something like
exercise, where getting someone really
upset or abject sadness are not things
that are not going to be valued in that
kind of situation. But there's still are a
variety of emotional levers that can be
pulled that can make the experience more
rich and certainly the joy. The, the sense
of accomplishment, the emotional
reinforcement that pushes people to play
more is important in most examples of
gamification. Narrative, the structure
that pulls together the pieces of the game
or the gamified system into some coherent
feeling whole. The narrative can be
explicit, the story line in a game. Or it
can be implicit and gamification doesn't
necessarily have the richness of the
aesthetic experiential aspect of games, to
put the work in creating a narrative. It
has to rely upon things like consistent
graphical experiences, creating a sense of
flow, and alluding to certain kinds of
practices or certain kinds of story ideas
that may be in players heads. Using those,
again, to tie together the individual
pieces. If there's no sense of narrative,
then the risk is that the gameified system
will just be a bunch of abstract stuff.
You get these badges. You get these points
but they're totally divorced from any
sense of coherence and relation to the
players life and that tends to limit the
effectiveness of gamification.
Progression, so here we are talking about
the notion that you start at one place and
you go up along the way until you get to
some higher place. Very important aspect
in, really, most examples of gamification,
is giving a player a sense that they are
going to had the opportunity to improve,
or at least to move from where they
started as oppose d to just doing the same
thing over and over and over again.
Progression doesn't necessarily requires,
specific examples like levels and points,
but those we see as typical. Game
components that get used to instantiate
that dynamic. And finally relationships.
People interacting with each-other.
Friends, teammates, opponents. Those
general level social dynamics that are
very important to the experience of the
game. So those are the dynamics. At the
next level are the game mechanics. These I
like to think of as the verbs of a game or
gamification. The elements that move the
action forward. Now with these and the
next set I won't go into detail on every
one because there more of them. That's the
notion of the pyramid that we have a few
dynamics. A larger number of mechanics and
a big number of components. But let me
just highlight a few of them. So things
like challenges. The game sets some
objective for you to reach. Chance.
There's some luck involved. Whether it's a
role of the dice or some other mechanism
that makes it so the result is random and
not entirely based on your activity. Both
cooperation and competition. Their
opposites, but both are valuable game
mechanics. Getting people to work
together, as well as to getting people to
compete against each other to have a
notion of winning and loosing. Feedback,
I've already talked about many times. Very
important for users to be able to see how
they are doing in real time because that
powerfully tends to drive them along to go
further. Resource acquisitions, so game
give you things, they give you opportunity
to get things in order to move the game
forward. Empires and Allies, for example,
let you acquire oil which then you need in
order to build things airplanes. Rewards,
some benefits that you get for some
achievement in the game, transactions.
Buying and selling, or exchanging
something with other players, or with
what's called a non player character, with
some automated character in the game.
Turns we saw with tic tac toe and win
states we also saw wi th tic tac toe. T he
state which defines winning the game. So,
again, these are various tools that can be
used to figure out how to move the action
forward. To get the players in the game to
go to one state to another. And then
finally the lowest level, most service
level kinds of game elements, are the game
components. Specific examples, specific
ways to do the higher level things that
dynamics and mechanics represent. So for
example, achievements, as opposed to just
the general notion of the challenge,
giving the players some reward attached to
doing a set of specific things, that's the
achievement. Avatar, showing the players
some visual representation of their
character. Badges, we're going to talk
more about these in a second. But specific
visual representations of those
achievements as well as of the higher
level dynamics in mechanics. Boss fights
is familiar if you play games, it may not
be if you don't. This is at the end of a
level, the end of some part of the game. A
really hard challenge. A high level
monster that you have to defeat, and it's
typically really hard to do so, in order
to get to the next level. Collections is
pulling together a bunch of different
things. Assembling certain pieces or
certain examples of something. You have to
get a whole bunch of spells together. Or,
you have to get a whole bunch of badges
together. To fill up a cabinet that you
get in the game. Combat is probably
familiar. Content unlocking means you need
to do something. Maybe an achievement.
Maybe some leveling up in order to get
access to certain new content in the game.
Gifting altruism. Giving things to other
people can actually make people want to
play the game more because it feels like
fun. People feel good about giving to
others. Leader boards I'll talk about
more. But, lists the players in order of
their score. Levels and points. Should be
fairly obvious but again I'll talk about
them more in a second. Eh. Quests are
similar to achievements. This is more the
kind of game-like notion that you have to
do some things that somehow a re
specifically defined within the structure
of the game. The social graph. We saw this
in Empires and Allies as well as at the
bottom in the Kias example. Seeing your
friends who are also in the game. And
allowing you to interact with them, to
play with and against them. Making the
game an extension of your social
networking experience. Teams, I already
talked about. Virtual goods. This we'll
see more of later on in the course, but
things within the game. Something that you
pick up, the powerful sword or the new
kind of house that you put on your
property in Zenga CityVille. Things that
are virtual, that are not real, but that
users are willing to pay either the
virtual currency of the game or the time
or even real money to get. So altogether
30 different game elements that have given
you. Again, not a universal comprehensive
list, but it should show you some of the
richness, some of the options that you
have to play with in implementing some
gamified system. And the structure of the
pyramid shows, first of all, that it goes
from narrow at top to broad at bottom. So
there are fewer dynamics than there are
components. But it also shows how the
lower level of examples, the points are
examples of things higher up. They are
examples of progression, and they may also
be examples of say, meritive. The lower
level examples are ways to do some of the
higher level things. That's how the
structure fits together.