Okay.
So you've learned about all of these
different game elements.
And in particularly the points, badges,
and leader boards.
You're done, right?
Wrong.
Game elements are a starting point for
gamification.
They are raw materials and tools you can
use and deploy.
But, just having them only gives you part
of what you need to know.
And frankly, a big problem with
gamification today.
Is that, many companies think that just
throwing elements onto a business process
magically makes something gamelike.
Magically makes it fun and engaging,
without doing any of the really hard
work.
And we'll look more at this objection and
what's accurate about it later on in the
course when I talk about the
pointsification argument about
gamification.
But for now, what's important is to
understand that, game elements are a
starting point.
But not the entirety of what you need to
do.
And if they were, then we would take
something like a frequent flyer program
and say, aha.
We've got the points.
We've got the rewards that you get in
terms of free travel.
You level up this person is premier
silver in this program.
And you get badges here for frequent
flyer miles.
It's the credit card representing your
different level.
The progress bars.
Remember the LinkedIn progress bar?
ha, people will love that.
Ooh, and status.
We haven't really talked about this yet.
But often, a claim that's made about
gamification is that it's very powerful.
Because people love to show off their
points and their badges and so forth.
So here we get premier status.
That sounds great.
Well that's all there was to it.
First of all, most people would spend all
of their time just in love with their
frequent flyer mile programs.
And constantly trying to play the
frequent flyer mile game when in fact
that's not really how people get this
experience at all.
People like getting frequent flyer miles
but, they don't think about it
necessarily as a really engaging game.
Except for a fairly small subset of
hardcore fliers who do everything they
can do optimize against their frequent
flyer program.
The larger point is that the elements are
not the game.
You'll recall earlier I said the
experience in the game are different.
Well, the elements in the game are
different as well.
The game, as I showed in that diagram is
the thing in between the elements and the
experience.
So if you just look at the elements, you
say oh, this site's got badges, great,
it's got achievements, great, it's got
quests, great.
That alone doesn't tell you whether it's
successful.
What makes the elements successful is the
way that they are all tied together.
And often, that involves recourse to some
of the higher level concepts, like the
dynamics.
You'll notice that points, badges, and
leader boards all exist at the base of
the pyramid.
They are service level components.
So, elements themselves don't tell you
that the experience is fun and engaging.
Second point.
If you focus too heavily on the elements,
especially on the PBLs.
There's a real tendency to over-emphasize
rewards.
And I'm going to talk about this in more
detail in the psychology section.
How it is that rewards can actually
demotivate.
So saying if you do this, you will get
either a badge or maybe even a cash
prize.
Can actually make people less likely to
engage in the activity and less likely to
really try their best.
But for now, it's sufficient to say
rewards are not the same thing as fun.
I described different theories of what
fun is.
And most of them included things other
than getting some reward.
Fun can be about interacting wtih
friends.
It can be about blowing off steam, it can
be about solving problems, it can be
about exploration.
Many different things can be fun.
The fact that you received a reward does
not necessarily mean that that experience
is fun.
And the fact that the experience is fun
doesn't necessarily mean that there's
some reward in it somewhere.
And while rewards are not a requirement
for the PBL kind of approach to
gamification.
They tend to be a dissenter of those
kinds of implementations.
And that's a flaw.
Again, the rewards themselves are not
necessarily wrong.
But if they're the only thing that the
designer focuses on is the objective.
Then there is a great danger that the
system will not actually generate the
true results which come from real
engagement.
And finally if you have points, badges
and leader boards in your site.
And that's the heart of it it's likely to
look somewhat like every other site that
has points, badges and leader boards.
And that causes two problems.
One is.
Users don't necessarily differentiate.
And the second is users get burned out.
They say, Wow.
I just went through collecting all these
badges in this other site.
Why do I have to start from scratch and
collect these badges here on this site?
It's not fun, even though the first time
I experienced it, I thought it was cool
and it attracted me to play more.
So a couple of common problems with In
particular, too much focus on PBLs in
gamification.
There are a variety of other reasons to
not stop with game elements.
And let me give you one example here.
And this comes from Google, which is an
extraordinarily good and successful
company in many ways.
But here's something that they
implemented which, to me, has not been
that great a success.
And it's called Google News Badges.
So Google in the summer of 2011 announced
that they would add a gamification
feature to Google News.
Hey, everyone's doing it.
And so what they said was as you surf
around and read news articles in Google
News.
Depending on the subject area of what you
read, you would get these badges.
This is a basketball badge because I read
a bunch of articles about basketball.
And these just pop up.
There's not a Google News Badges site you
go to.
You just find them, suddenly you read a
bunch of basketball articles.
And Google has a whole bunch of reasons
why this is good for you.
It's a way of track of what you're
reading.
It's a way of showing people what you're
It's a way of showing things to your
friends.
It's a way of getting some data about how
many articles you've read in a certain
compared to everyone else.
But none of these to me seem terribly
compelling.
If I like reading articles about
basketball I don't necessarily need the
news badge to tell me I've read a bunch
of articles about basketball and even if
it does.
So what?
The badges also are not really giving me
any kind of reward or achievement.
They're just there.
They're looking like the kind of PBL
badges that recognize some
accomplishment.
But here the accomplishment is just I
happened to read a bunch of articles on
the same topic.
So it's not clear to me how Google News
Badges.
Truly motivates and engages Google news
readers to do anything that they wouldn't
already do.
And indeed Google recently announced that
it had gotten rid of the News Badges
feature entirely.
So what went wrong?
It seems like they saw the appeal of
gamification and just thought they would
try it out in this way.
And that's dangerous, because it leads
you to put things into sites that don't
have a direct connection to driving real
business value.
And when I get to the design section,
I'll talk about how to think about those
kinds of questions first, rather than
putting in the elements and going from
there.
A few more points to drive home, this
concept that the elements.
Well they may be useful, and they're a
good starting board for gamification,
they're not the game itself.
Because, if you just focus on these
elements.
What about those meaningful choices which
make something game-like?
Just deciding to click one time versus
click a hundred times, or deciding to,
watch a video over here versus do
something over here on the site.
It isn't really a choice that feels
weighty.
It feels like it's something that the
person has to think about and make a good
choice or a bad choice.
it's not something that really
necessarily engages the user.
Similarly, challenges are not necessarily
puzzles.
So saying that you have to do something
and something that may take more effort.
So for example, clicking 1000 times takes
a lot more effort than clicking one time.
But clicking 1000 times isn't
challenging.
It's certainly not what we think of as a
puzzle, something that requires problem
solving and thought in creativity to
overcome.
Now not every game of[UNKNOWN] has those.
And they're not well suited to every
single example.
But if you can create something that
feels like a puzzle, our brains love
those things.
I don't mean just a jigsaw puzzle or
logic puzzle.
But something that feels like there's
some challenge.
There's some creativity that you're
called upon to deploy.
Is something that's going to be much more
powerful than something that just
requires mere effort.
Third, what about mastery?
The fact that you can get a bunch of
badges and get a bunch of points.
Is there really a pathway, to true
competence.
To being an expert at something or not.
If it's just a staircase for the sake of
having a staircase.
It may have some value, it may attract
people.
But it's not going to be as rich and
engaging as something that has an
opportunity to truly master some kind of
skill.
Whatever that skill is?
Community.
As I talked about a few times.
Social interactions are tremendously
powerful in games.
And often, these PBL type sites have no
notion of interaction with other people.
You're just going and collecting things
just for it's own sake.
And finally, people are different.
So if there is just one kind of
structure.
That gives people a set of tasks to
overcome.
Is it really going to pull in peope with
different sorts of motivations.
People with different sorts of
conceptions of fun.
So these are some of the limitations of a
purely element focused approach.
I put this whole unit in on game elements
because they are important.
And you need to understand what they are
to start down the path of gamification.
But you can't stop there.