Up until now I've been talking about games
in a very general, abstract sense, because
gamification draws upon basic principles
that are common to all games. But it also
draws specifically upon a certain category
of games namely, video games. And most of
the gamification examples that we're going
to think about, involve online digital
systems which are directly related to what
we see in video games. So, it's worth
understanding the video game industry.
Also because the size of it and the scale
of it and the pervasiveness of it are part
of why the motifs of gamification are so
familiar. So, we start 40 years ago, 1972
or so with Pong. The first mass market
successful video game still gives me
chills. Here it is. Pong was a revolution
play. There it is. Because it allowed
people to interact with what was on their
screen. If, by today's standards of course
was unbelievably primitive and it's hard
to imagine how anyone would get interested
in what you see behind me on the screen
there. But Pong for the first time, gave
people the power to interact with a
digital game at home. And since then, the
video game industry has grown and grown,
and now as I said, It's 40 years old. It
is both substantial as a business
phenomenon, pervasive in the experience of
especially the younger generation of
people particularly in the west but in
many other parts of the world as well. And
video games have developed a very
sophisticated language of how to express
themselves, and entertain and engage
people. Here's one example just to show
what I'm talking about here. This is
Cityville, one of the casual social games
on Facebook made by Zinga. And Cityville
as you can see is clearly a game and a
fairly graphically simple game. At least
compare to some of the rich 3D immersive
games that we have on consoles and PCs
today. Here's the interesting thing about
Cityville. Cityville was launched by Zynga
in 2011. In 41 days, it hit a hundred
million registered users. Six Weeks. Zero
to a, a hundred million registered users.
An extraor dinary rate of growth and it's
not limited to just this one game or this
one company. This is a huge phenomenon.
So, here's some statistics to capture just
how big the video game industry is today.
The industry depending on who's numbers
you take is somewhere on the order of 60
to 80 billion dollars a year in revenues.
Double the revenues of Hollywood from box
office sales of films. Films make money
from other mechanism as well, including
tie ins with games. But if you talk about
box office revenues games are already much
bigger and their growing faster than
Hollywood. The second is that games are
evolving to the point where online games,
games played or distributed online as
opposed to on consoles like the Play
Station and XBox and Nintendo Wii. Or
downloaded in a box and loaded on a PC.
The online games are growing faster and
are poised. To become the biggest segment
of the games marketplace, and
interestingly, already the biggest
component of the online games marketplace
is China. So it's not just an American or
a Western phenomenon. The third is that
games are becoming the foundation for
other industries. Virtual goods, I will
talk about later in the class, but these
are things that you can buy within the
game. Think about a brand new sword for a
player in a massively multi-player online
game. Or some additional seeds and other
equipment that you might use in a Zynga
game like Farmville. Things that you pay
real money for that appear in the game.
This economy around virtual goods is
already many billions of dollars, 7.3
billion globally and two billion in the
US, according to the latest statistics I
could find. A very substantial market
which is not games themselves but
something built on top of the great
success of games. And finally the other
great evolution is the rise of mobile
games. This was a study early in 2012 that
found that 44 percent of people, US and
UK, have played a mobile game something
like an Angry Birds on their smartphone in
the last month. So, the games industry is
big and it's developing. And I think it's
fair to talk about it as the mass medium
of the twenty-first century. Here are just
a few statistics about usage numbers. If
you look at things like the Zynga Games,
lots of people. I talked about a hundred
million on Cityville 250 million, quarter
of a billion unique registered users, and
that it was already probably a few months
old. They've surpassed that. Angry Birds
alone over a hundred million. Xbox LIVE
games 35, World of Warcraft over ten
million players. World of Warcraft, those
are paying players, so that's even more
important in terms of monetization. The
other important piece though is how much
time people are using these things. And so
those ten million World of Warcraft
players up here, if you look at the amount
of time they spend, it's actually huge.
It's 50 billion minutes a month because
they're playing for long periods of time.
Where as something like Angry Birds, even
though it has a higher user base is only a
mere twelve billion minutes a month that
people are playing because people use it
less. Still a pretty big number. And if
you look at something like the Xbox Live
games, which are the core console games so
therefore games people play more. 120
billion minutes a month. So, figure out
how much that is across the player base,
and figure out how much time that actually
represents relative to traditional media.
It's not the same thing as people having
their television on for seven hours a day
in the time, but this is interactive time
it's time when the player is directly
engaged in playing the game. Big, big
numbers. So, the important thing here to
take away is that games are a mass
phenomenon. And just to correct a
misunderstanding that people sometimes
have, they are not just a mass phenomenon
for teenage boys. It's true that the
highest percentage of gamers is teenagers
and young adults, twelve to seventeen year
olds in the US. This study by the Peer
Research Foundation found 97 percent play
some kind of video game. Virtually
everyone. But it's not just them. And the
Entertainment Software Association has f
ound that the average gamer is actually 30
years old. And if you know anything about
averages, that means there's a whole lot
of them that are older than 30. Moreover
it's not just boys or men. Almost half of
all video game players today are women.
There are some skewing effects. Women
generally speaking tend to play more the
social, casual games. Men tend to play
more of the first person shooter types of
games. But overall if you talk about video
games as an experience, as a mass medium,
as a phenomenon that people are conversant
with and familiar with, it cuts across all
those boundaries. And the final point is
that video games are not just going in and
guns blazing blowing something up and
shooting things. Sure, there are games
that involve that. And some of them have
been very successful. But especially in
recent years, we've seen the rise of many
different categories of games that are
very different. So for example, the
Sandbox games things like Minecraft, which
if you're not familiar with you should go
check out. Minecraft is a game that was
written by a single developer that is
incredibly rudimentary in terms of its
graphics, has no purpose. You go into
Minecraft, you're given a world. And you
have to dig things up and find different
kinds of ore and chop down trees and do
other things to create raw materials and
then put them together in different ways
and build things. Why? Well, because it's
fun. And it turns out that Minecraft has
been a sensation. Huge numbers of users
voluntarily pay money to play this game.
Which or, and most of the time that they
were doing so was far from finish. It was
expressly in alpha or beta form, people
found this incredibly compelling. In part
because they could share their creations
with other people. It gave them a huge
Sandbox. You could make anything you want
in Minecraft. Another category are the
building games, or here I mentioned
already, Civilization by Sid Meier, the
SimCity games by Will Wright, games that
let you create and build things. Again,
not to kill them. But to figure out how
your actions in running a complex system
like a city or like a nation state create
results as they interact with each other
and with other parts of the system. A
derivative of those are what I'll call
social building games. Here's where we see
things like Farmville and the Sims. Games
that have that construction building
element, but also involve collaborating
with and interacting with other players in
the game. Showing off what you're doing
for other players, having a social
dimension in addition to that building
dimension. Very popular, very successful.
Then we have the massively multiplayer
online games, things like World of
Warcraft, which again have been quite
successful and do have some measure of
running around and killing things but also
have guilds and communities, and things
like auction houses and things like
leveling up characters in different skill
areas and crafting and exploring worlds. A
rich experience much more than just the
pure competitive, pure destruction element
of games. And finally, puzzle games,
things like Angry Birds, where you have to
figure out how do I pull this slingshot
just the right way to knock over the
structure. Or Portal and Portal two, very
successful hit game in recent years, in
which the player has to figure out how to
create holes in a wall that when you put
them together solve a puzzle of how to get
out of a room. If you haven't played go
and look at some YouTube videos or some
information on the game. Really
successful, powerful game using simple
kinds of problem solving mechanics. And
the point here is that these are not
outliers or exceptions. These in many
cases are the most successful game
releases in recent years. So, games are,
big. They are sophisticated. They are
pervasive across modern life, and they are
diverse. They are not just as simple as
you might think and they are not just
about graphics. They're about all these
different forms of interaction
individually and socially.