An important question that arises in
enterprise gamification is whether the
game is truly voluntary. And one way to
describe that is the word Playbor which is
the combination of play and labor. If
it's, both play and work at the same time,
what is it? Is it a game? Well, under the
definition of games that I gave you, it's
not. A game has to be voluntary. That's at
the essence of what makes something game
like the fact that you choose to play and
you choose to take the rules of the game
seriously. If someone says, go play this
game right now, then you don't necessarily
have a choice. If you're forced to do it,
you may be going through the same motions.
If, let's say, you're an actor hired to
play a game of soccer in a movie, you're
not playing soccer when you're acting out
your role, you're acting out your role.
So, what about someone who is forced to
play a game at work, or more commonly, is
forced to engage in some gamified activity
at work? What if they don't have agency
and choice over the matter but their
employer puts into place a gamified system
to incentivize them to work harder and be
more productive? What about, for example,
these checkout cashiers at Target who have
the screen here that you see in front of
you when they are checking people out at
the store. The screen has a system that
gives you either green, red or yellow
based on how fast you check someone out.
So this person that just got checked out,
they got a G. They did well, they did that
fast enough. You see your last ten scores,
you see your total scores. This person has
88 percent G and other information. Now,
you can look at that and say great. That's
incentivizing those target check out
clerks to do a better job. It's making it
a little bit more fun for them. It's
giving them some extra added incentive to
do a better performance on their task. Or
you can look at it and say, wait a minute.
First of all, this is not about the
cashiers at all. It's about the company
monitoring them down to the level of every
individual checkout. So it's this kind of
private big brother looking over your
shoulder constantly every second as you're
at work. And secondly, it's not at all
about fun or about voluntariness Or about,
meaning or anything for the employee. It's
purely about, external extrinsic controls.
It's purely about, we will reward you if
you do well or maybe even more so, we will
punish you if you don't do as well. And
where's the play, where's the game aspect
in that? So, there's a real question here.
At the conceptual level about whether
these are gameification. But more, more
importantly at the practical level, are
these a good idea? And are these mandatory
systems truly fair and appropriate and
ethical for the workers? Here's another
example to take a look at. This is an
article from the Los Angeles Times. If you
want to read the actual article you can
get it here. It's a story about a group of
laundry workers and housekeeping staff at
hotels at Disneyland. And Disney has put
into place at these hotels a leader board
system. So, as they are doing the laundry
in the basement of these hotel, they see
how quickly every member of the
housekeeping staff is cleaning rooms, and
performing their other assigned duties and
there's a leader board and a ranking that
shows them in that way. And the employees
have a name for this system. They don't
call it a game, they don't call it a
leader board, they call it the Electronic
Whip. It's something that they perceive as
standing over them, threatening them with
punishment and goading them on to work
harder. Here's a couple of quotes from the
story to get you thinking about whether
this is the kind of practice that should
be encouraged or potentially if it's the
kind of practice that necessarily will
follow as gamification takes hold in the
enterprise. Here is a quote from one of
the workers saying, I was nervous and felt
I was being controlled even more. So, this
ties in very directly to what I talked
about with regard to self determination
theory. Part of what makes something intri
nsically motivating is when the person
feels autonomy. They feel like they are in
control of the situation. If the feedback
that they get doesn't promote that, that
autonomy. If it's not purely
informational, but it's perceived as
controlling, it's feedback saying, we are
using this to tell you what to do and to
make you do what we want, then it does not
promote intrinsic motivation. And then,
actually, it can demotivate. It can lead
to worse performance. Here's a couple more
quotes. What were the effects of this
electronic whip system according to the
workers? Well, it led to a sort of
competition. Great, competition. The
workers see the leader-board, and without
being told anything more, they figure out
that this is a game, and they try to play
the game, and try to score high. And some
of the workers tried to race to the head
of the pack. So you might think, okay,
great, this is working the way it should,
but here's the kicker. That lead to
dissension and made other employees worry
that a reasonable pace wouldn't be enough
to keep the boss happy. Is that really
what we want? Is that really even in the
interest of the company in terms of
promoting a successful and effective
workforce. And final quote here, according
to some of the workers, employees have
been known to skip bathroom breaks, out of
fear that their production will fall and
managers will demand an explanation. All
of this just from a leader board. So, it's
important to think about, first of all,
how can gamified systems in the enterprise
be designed to promote the beneficial
aspects of gamification but not lead to
this kind of lord of the flies, all
against all competition that demoralizes
workers and likely based on the research
about intrinsic motivation, likely will
lead to worse performance than they had
before. How do companies avoid that and
still get the benefits that we've talked
about from gamification in the enterprise?
One aspect is the extent to which the
system is voluntary. And is perceived as
voluntary by the workers, and is perceived
as transparent. What is this doing? Is
this actually tracking me for something
that will be used in assessing my job
performance? Or is this just
informational, to help encourage me to do
a better job? And, what are the elements
of the gamified system that are being
employed? As we talked about, a pure
leader board, a pure ranking and scoring
system is probably the worst way to
promote the beneficial, cooperative,
engaging aspects of gamification. And
instead, promote the more vicious and
harmful kinds of gamification among
workers. Beyond that, I leave it you to
think about this question but it's an
important one for any company to take into
account when going down the path of
putting game-like systems into their
workplace.