An important question for enterprise
gamification is, what actually motivates
people in the workplace? So, there are all
of the standard kinds of things. Your
salary, bonuses, stock options, verbal
praise from your supervisors, promotions,
more job responsibility. All the
traditional kinds of levers of
compensation that get used in the
workplace to encourage people to work. But
hopefully, if you've been listening to the
course so far, you realized that these are
almost entirely extrinsic motivators. They
are not things that are about the inherant
joy and pleasure and engagement of the
work. They are external rewards that are
designed as compensation. Think about what
the word compensation means. It's
something you'll have to get to compensate
you. Before doing something that you don't
really want to do, i.e. Work. So, there is
nothing wrong with that, of course, that's
how salaries work everywhere and they're
going to be the core element of how
people, get motivated to do jobs for most
people, but there's more to the story than
that. There's something beyond working for
external rewards, and that's where
gamification has a real opportunity if
it's designed in the ways I've talked
about to focus on producing engaging
experience and at activating intrinsic
motivation. So, let's look at a few
different ways that gamification can
motivate people at work outside of chasing
rewards. One Is learning, or skill
development. That might be in order to
obtain some of those extrinsic rewards. If
you had better skills you get a higher
salary or you get promoted to a better job
or maybe you get a better job somewhere
else. But learning as I've talked about is
also about problem solving and it's about
engaging those parts of your brain that
love to figure out new things. So, skill
development in the workplace can take
advantage of gamification in a way that is
helpful for the employees and also
beneficial for the companies. What I've
highlighted here is a screenshot from a
service by Live Ops, which is an
out-source cal l center operator. What
Live Ops does is they essentially create
virtual call centers by stitching together
people working at home using an
application to act as though they're part
of a virtual part of a call center. And so
Live Ops has lots of people working
part-time for them. Stay at home moms.
People who are out of work. People who
pick up an hour here, an hour there.
Answering calls or making outbound calls
for the call center from home and
therefore people who are often eager to
develop new skills if it can be done in a
flexible way that fits in with their
situation. So Live Ops has built their own
gamified site. It's got the usual kinds of
trophies and badges, it's got the feedback
metrics about what people are doing,
points, all of the usual things, but it's
very much geared towards skill
development. It's geared not as much
towards, we want you to get off this call
that you're on with a customer quickly and
in a way that makes the customer happy
which was the other call center example I
talked to you about. This is much more
about we want to help you learn how to be
better at this job. How to learn different
aspects of the job and how to be effective
in a way that will then move you up, in a
way that's recognized by the badges and
achievements and so forth, and then
potentially help you on the path to your
success in your career. So, that's one
motivator that lots of companies, have for
their employees, the opportunity to learn
things and skill up. Next is information.
So, what's the value of information to an
employee? Well, employees don't always
know how they're doing. Performance review
every six months, every year, and that's
very far removed from the day to day
process of your work. You get feedback
from your coworkers, and your boss and so
forth, but many employees don't really
have any sense about the quality of their
work and certainly no ability to directly
turn that back around and take advantage
of situations where they are doing a good
job. This is a screenshot fr om a company
called Objective Logistics which does
gamification, initially targeted at the
restaurant industry. So, they provide a
dashboard for restaurants to use for their
servers where they can track how the
servers are doing. What tip, what check
size they're getting and what their
performance is. And they can then provide
feedback to the employees about how
they're doing in this weeks challenge is
sell a bunch of the dinner entrees and so
forth. There are various metrics that are
put on here. There's summaries about your
ranking on the leaderboard, and how much
you earned in extra tips. All of this
provides information to the server and it
provides information to the company and
the company can use this in order to
target the best shifts to the employees
who are doing the best job which motivates
the employees to do a better job to get
the better work opportunities and also
gives them a much more concrete sense of
what their performance is. It activates
the competitive instinct and the desire to
chase the reward but it also paints a
better picture for the employee, connects
up very directly what they are doing via
feedback to the way that the company
treats them. The next one is corporate
citizenship. So, this I'll talk about in
more detail in a subsequent segment. But
there are things that you do sometimes in
a company that are not necessarily about
your job. Great example is the language
quality game from Microsoft that I used as
one of the early examples where they got
employees to review all of these dialogue
boxes for Windows localization in
different languages. And I told you that
thousands of Microsoft employees did this
voluntarily. Why? Well part of it was just
the inherent fun of the game, part of it
was competition to want to beat the other
offices. But part of it was a sense that
they were doing something that was good
for the company. They were helping
Microsoft make better products by removing
bugs and errors in the localization of
windows. And that's something that peop le
who are part of an organization, part of a
team, feel some resonance with. They are
not going to work as a volunteer for weeks
on end just for the company's good but
they want to take pride in their work and
their workplace and they want to be good
corporate citizens. So, that's a motivator
that can be used for gamification.
Finally, last but certainly not least.
What about fun? What's the role of fun in
the workplace? Well there're lots of
benefits of fun in the workplace. Creating
a more congenial environment, promoting
teamwork, so on, and so forth. But there
are opportunities to specifically use fun
to achieve direct workplace benefits. This
is something called the Face Game at
Zappos. And if you want to see more
details there's a little video here about
this. Zappos is an online retailer
initially of shoes and now of other
clothing-type items that's part of
amazon.com now Amazon bought it for
roughly a billion dollars. And Zappos, as
we'll talk about, is a very fun workplace.
This is something that they created called
the Face Game for their employees. When
you log onto the company Internet, after
you type in your name and password, you
get shown a picture of someone who's one
of your coworkers randomly selected. And
you get to say, "Who is this?" And you can
fill in this is Ronda", or you can say "I
have no clue, don't know who this is". And
what the game does is once you do that,
either says "congratulations you got it
right, it is Ronda", or it says "Nope.
That was actually Brenda" and we'll give
you Brenda's profile page in the company
internet. So, what this does is creates a
little bit of fun and helps people get to
know their coworkers, helps them find out
more about the people who work with, with
them, what they do, where they work, what
their skills are which can be valuable in
terms of promoting better collaboration
and teamwork within the organization. All
based on leveraging off of fun.