There is an interesting and important
distinction that comes up in enterprise
gamification, which is the dividing line
between the game on one side and the job
on the other. Why is this important? Well,
it's important for a number of reasons.
But the core is that, if you're designing
a gamified system in the enterprise, what
you hear about is ultimately the job. The
goal is to motivate employees to do
something that's a business benefit. The
game is a means to that end. But for the
players, for the employees, they may well
be focused on the game. The game is the
thing that engages them. And to the extent
that there's a diversion, to the extent
that the game is pushing them one way and
the job is pushing them another way that
leads to real problems because again, the
players have a strong tendency to go in
the direction that the game pushes them as
opposed to what their job really should be
about. So, think about as an example, a
call center. And the call center sets up a
game or a gamified system using points and
badges and leader boards and so forth as
we, as we've seen. And then sets the rules
of the game with something like, if you
get done with a call complete a call in
less than 30 seconds, you get ten points.
And if you complete more than a certain
number of calls in an hour, you get 50
points, and so on and so forth. And all of
the structures in the game are around the
volume and the speed of the calls. What
are people going to do? The call center
agents are going to try to get customers
off the phone as fast as they possibly
can. Not to provide good service to them,
but just to get them off the phone to
optimize against the game. On the other
hand, if you have the same gamified
structure, but the points are for things
like good customer satisfaction. So the
customer says that, you did a great job
when they get surveyed afterwards, you get
100 points for that. And that's what the
game rewards, or, you get a bonus reward
if you get a streak of customer sat, you
got above a certain level in customer
satisfaction, five calls in a row, you get
500 bonus points. Then the game is
encouraging people to optimize on
satisfaction. Now, we still don't know in
this very general hypothetical whether
this matches up perfectly with the job
requirements. So certainly, if the system
is designed just to create call center
agents who want to get customers off the
phone as fast as possible at any cost,
that's not likely to be something that
companies are going to want. At least
companies that are thoughtful how their
long term interest in their customer
perceptions. But the question about how
important it is to optimize on customer
satisfaction versus something else is a
busineness, business decision that the
company ultimately that, that is the
customer of the call center or the company
operating the call center needs to figure
out. And then the structures of the
gamified system have to be designed to
motivate towards those business goals. So,
this ties back in to the element of the
design framework that I gave you earlier
on to first figure out what the business
goals are, and then go through the
gamification process. It's always
important to focus on the job, or the task
at hand because otherwise, people will
optimize themselves on the game. The
second dimension here is that sometimes
people are motivated at work for things
outside the job in a good way. And that
refers to corporate citizenship,
citizenship behaviors, situations where
people will do things at work just to be
nice to colleagues or to be good for the
company. So, some of the ones that get
mentioned here Altruism, people will do
things just to be good to other people.
Consciousness, people will work hard and
want to do good job just because they take
pride in what they do. Civic Virtue, a
sense that you are part of a larger
community and you care about doing your
part for the community, even though it's a
business community where you work as
opposed to a social community at home.
Common Courtesy and Sportsmanship being
fair to others. These are n ormal human
motivations, and they're true for people
at work as well. And, they can be tapped
into for the benefit of the company. In
various examples using gamification, the
one that I gave you before was the
Microsoft Language Quality game, which
tapped into people's desire to make
Windows a better product by volunteering
their time to find localization bugs. Ross
Smith, who is the head of the test group
at Microsoft that implimented the language
quality game and several other
productivity games, has developed a
framework to understand which applications
lend themselves well to this approach. And
his structure involves two different kinds
of behavior or tasks, and three different
kinds of skills. So the two kinds of
behavior are first, what he calls In-Role
behavior, i.e. What you're doing for your
job. It's something that's part of your
normal job description. And then
Citizenship behaviors, things that you do
at work to be a good employee, a good
citizen of the organization, not
necessarily the specific things that you
are hired to do and compensated for. And
then he talks about, three different
categories of skills. One set or what he
calls Core Skills which are skills that
everyone in the organization has. The next
are Unique Skills, skills that are limited
to a particular employee or group of, of
employees. And next, Future Skills, skills
that an employee would like to obtain. And
Smith says, these productivity games,
Things like the language quality game
designed to improve productivity in the
workplace are best used in just two of the
sections of this chart. The first one is
for core roles that involve citizenship
behavior or core skills I should say, that
involve citizenship behavior. And this is
where the language quality game fits. So,
this is a skill that everyone in the
company has, the skill is speaking your
own language. It doesn't require anything
unique to you, any particular training.
Anyone who is a native speaker of the
language where the office is can easily
review dialogue boxes in their n ative
language. And they're going to do it not
because it's their job but because it's
part of being a good corporate citizen.
So, the fact that the language quality
game is down here and not an in role kind
of task. Is what enables it. Because if
it's a core skill and it's an in-role kind
of task is what enables it because if it's
a core skill and it's an in-role kind of
task then there's not as good a fit for
something that is designed to be fun and
game-like. The only reason to motivate you
to do something that everyone in the
company can do is if it's part of this
kind of collaborative activity. The other
category where he says gamification or
productivity games work well is up here.
So, it's in-role. It's your actual job
responsibilities but it's about future
skills. It's about things that you want to
learn how to do. That's where gamification
and productivity games can help in terms
of training and improving people's
behavior. Really what I think Smith is
getting at here is that there are two big
categories of gamification application to
the workplace. One involves groups, it
involves community. Trying to get
participation from as many people as
possible within the organization. The
other involves individuals and typically
involves improving their skills or
improving their performance at work. Those
are very different and one is better done
in an, an example that's focused on actual
job responsibilities, and one is better
done outside of that environment. If it,
the situation though involves unique
skills, people's unique capabilities but
it's skills they already have, a game-like
structure may not be as effective because
it doesn't create a level playing field
for people to interact on. If it's not
about training and problem solving but
just showing what you can do, then there's
not really an environment for a game or
for a proper application of gamification.
So, all of this goes to emphasize the
point that enterprise gamification
requires a close attention to the nature
of the game and how that match es up with
the different sorts of objectives and
motivations in the workplace.