This week, we're going to work at some
specific applications of gamefication.
Many of the examples I've given you are in
the external gamefication bucket. They're
about customer facing types of uses. In
this unit I'm going to look at internal
gamefication and specifically,
gamefication in the enterprise. In a large
business organization. Many major
enterprises are starting to experiment
with gamefication and to apply it in
concrete situations. Sometimes consciously
thinking that they are trying to gamify a
process, sometimes just using a technique
that seems to work that when we look at
it, we would identify as being part of
gamification. The research firm
Constellation Research, put out a report
at the end of last year, where they talked
to 55 different early adopters of
enterprise gamification and found a wide
range of different kinds of uses within
the enterprise. I'd like to highlight few
examples for you, major areas where I see
potential take up by enterprises and give
you an example for each of them. The first
is intranets or extranets, online
collaboration systems that companies
operate for their employees or their
extended networks. And gamification works
here just like it does in external setting
with a discussion forum like
StackOverflow. The game elements can be
used to encourage people to contribute, to
encourage people to comment and respond,
to enhance the quality of the
participation that people engage in, and
to develop leader boards to identify
people who have the most expertise or the
most involvement in certain topics. So,
here you see a set of leader boards for
the SAP Community network, which is the
extra net for the Enterprise software
company, SAP and their network of
developers that interact with SAP software
at other companies. And they very
actively, use gamification techniques to
enhance the quality of the discussion in
that forum. So, that's an enterprise case
because it is being used internally by an
enterprise, but the same basic dynamics
that we saw in StackOverflow and re ally
any other discussion forum kind of
application. The next one though is
different. This is about productivity, and
when I say productivity enhancement, I
mean, helping or encouraging employees to
do their core job better. There are many
different examples of this and there are
many different kinds of jobs. So, what it
takes to motivate a sales person maybe
different from what it takes to motivate
an accountant or a financial analyst. But,
in almost every case, gamification can
produce motivation and can provide
information and feedback that is valuable
to employees and helps them improve their
job performance. Here's one concrete
example which comes from call centers. So,
call centers have large numbers of agents
and they have to encourage those agents
to, first of all, deal with calls quickly
because the longer they're on the phone,
the more cost there is for the customer.
And at the same time they want to
encourage the agents to deal with
customers well because the ultimate
customers, the customers of the people
using the call center business will tend
to be upset if the agent is clueless or
surly or anything like that. So, the call
center operators are starting to look to
gamification as a technique to help them
manage these customer service agents
better. This is an example from a start-up
called Arcarus which is specifically
focused on this call center enterprise
market. And you see here on the right, a
screen that would come up for an agent and
it's got a leader board, she's number one.
It's got a set of levels that she can
achieve by virtue of her various
activities on dealing with calls. It's got
some customer satisfaction numbers that
show some data on how she's doing and it's
got achievement. So all the standard
gamification elements but here, focused in
specifically on encouraging better
performance for a customer service agent
and highlighting the key elements and
designed in an aesthetic way that works
for that application. This here that you
see on the left is a screen that the
company might ge t looking at key
performance indicators, that's what KPI
stands for, and integrating in those
business metrics with the data coming out
of the gamification engine allowing them
to monitor their employee performance and
use the gamification system to improve the
level of productivity. Now, let me put a
placeholder here which I'm going to expand
on later that there's a danger in this
kind of application. That the gamified
system could actually rather than helping
the call center agents be a tool for
oppressing them and constantly monitoring
their work in a way that's not helpful to
them. So let's keep that in mind as a risk
but it certainly can be done in a positive
way, which I think this is an example of.
Next category I'll call efficiency
enhancement. The difference between
productivity and efficiency here is
productivity is in someone's core job
responsibility. Efficiency is just about
making them work better by doing
everything they do at work efficiently,
and specifically, the example I want to
talk about is e-mail. So lots and lots of
workers spend time in their e-mail. And
it's not their job primarily to answer
e-mail, but they have to do it as part of
their job. And people waste tons and tons
of time, countless hours answering e-mail,
getting e-mail that's irrelevant, cleaning
out their mailbox, and so forth. And so,
gamification is being used to improve the
efficiency of that process. The example
that I show you here is the E-mail Game
from a company called Baden. And you see
here they've got a timer so you see how
much time you're spending in your e-mail.
You see this progress bar of how much
you've got left and you see a point
system. And the way the E-mail Game works
is you get points for quickly disposing of
your e-mail. For deleting it or responding
to it in a way that you can take it out of
your inbox. It incentivizes and encourages
you to deal with e-mail efficiently. And
that little nudge tends to give people
enough reason to deal with their e-mail in
a more efficient way. Saving lots and lot
s of time that gets freed up for other
things. Another interesting approach to
e-mail is being taken by a company called,
Seriosity, that has a system called a Tent
and their idea was to create a virtual
currency around e-mail. So they created a
set of tokens that you attach to e-mail
and it cost you this virtual currency to
send and receive e-mail. And the idea is
by creating this kind of virtual economy,
people will start to think about whether
it's worth sending an e-mail. Well, if it
actually cost something, only got so many
resources and I have to use some of them
to send this e-mail, do I really want to
send all to the whole company about this
particular irrelevant thing or not? And so
the idea here is that by creating a
structure that provides feedback and the
ability to manipulate the activity around
e-mail in a game-like way, people will
start to see their effects on the overall
system. That kind of system's thinking
that games can encourage and therefore be
more responsible about the email that they
send and receive. So a different approach
tackling a similar problem and there other
problems in the efficiency domain as well.
Situations where gamification can be used
to encourage people to waste less time and
therefore have more time for their core
jobs. The next one I don't have a
screenshot for but this is an example from
Deloitte where they an application called
WhoWhatWhere, that is used to encourage
their consultants to find out more about
each other. That's in the broad domain of
knowledge management. Companies don't
necessarily collaborate internally that
well. Especially a very knowledge oriented
company like a consulting firm has people
all over the world with tremendous amounts
of knowledge about customers and about
topics and yet, they don't necessarily
know about each other. And it would be
really helpful for the company if when a
consultant in Cleveland had a question
about say, supply chain process
improvements in the oil and gas industry,
that they would be able to quickly see who
else in my company has worked on those
engagements or who else has real knowledge
about that area. So, gamification can be a
way of encouraging people to provide that
information into the system and
facilitating a process that encourages
that kind of sharing. The WhoWhatWhere
system at Deloitte does that by creating
game mechanics around the consultants
sharing information about what they're
doing on their existing enterprise
collaboration system. And other companies
are starting to use similar kinds of
applications to encourage that kind of
lightweight knowledge sharing. There are a
variety of applications in Human
Resources. Let me touch on a few of them
really quickly. Companies are using
gamification for hiring. Just playing
games sometimes tells you something about
people and gamified systems can be used to
identify the best candidates and to review
candidates in the hiring process.
Onboarding. Gamification is a way to get
people up and running at a company. Early
on, we talked about onboarding as an
important technique in game design. So if
you think about your HR process as a kind
of game, gamification and game techniques
can be used to onboard employees quickly.
Beyond onboarding is Acculturation,
getting people engaged in the culture of
the enterprise. And games, by creating a
fun kind of collaborative environment, can
help people get a sense of their
co-workers and the notion of working
together as a team and can be a way to
reinforce the culture of the organization.
Now, if the culture of the organization is
very formal and serious, then a game-like
system may not be the best way to do it.
But if not, or in a wide variety of other
contexts, a game-like system may be a
great way to ease people into a sense of
how we do things here and what the nature
is of our culture. Corporate training easy
way to see that, that applies to
gamification using game mechanics to
encourage people and reward people for the
learning that they do within the
organization and various kinds of training
programs. Performance review and employee
recognition. When we hear from Daniel
Debow who I'll do an interview with later
in this segment, his company uses
gamification for informal employee
rewards. Telling people you did a great
job in the enterprise and providing a
structure around that activity and have it
renowned to the benefit of the company. We
can also think of gamification being used
in the more structured, formal process of
performance reviews, by expanding out to
things like badges and achievements and
other forms of recognition. And by
encouraging employees to contribute to 360
reviews of their co-workers. And finally
T&E, travel and entertainment. Here's an
example from Google. For their travel and
entertainment reimbursement they give
people a fixed amount that they can
recover for a particular two city travel
pair they went, that they were traveling
to. And then what they do is they create a
virtual economy. So if you don't use the
full amount you're granted, you can bank
it, you can give it to charity or you can
cash it out, though at a discount. And
this makes that kind of credit liquid in a
way, which encourages people to think
about creatively using it. To be more
efficient about their use of that travel
and entertainment currency which
previously employees didn't think about as
a currency or a game at all. They just
thought about it as a process of getting
reimbursement. Here employees are
encouraged to think about how to spend
efficiently because then they bank
additional currency that they can use
either for themselves or for charitable
donations. Next one is innovation.
Companies want to encourage their
employees to come up with great new ideas.
So this is an example from the Department
of Work and Pensions in the UK, a public
governmental organization not necessarily
the kind of organization known for great
innovation. What they've done is they
built something called Idea Street which
is an idea market place. So, to encourage
people within their organization to come
up w ith great ideas to improve their
service, they created a virtual stock
market. So, employees come up with ideas
and you can see some ideas here. And other
employees can essentially buy and sell
shares in those ideas. There's a price,
daily change, volume, total market cap.
And here's the link where you can buy and
sell it. And they've created a
stock-market-like marketplace around these
ideas. So, great ideas start to float to
the top. People can join in on teams that
have ideas that they think are cool and
that are effective and that encourages
more activity on those ideas and what they
found is they've generated a large number
of ideas that have actually been put into
place in the organization saving millions
of dollars, or millions of pounds in the
UK, and actually delivering better service
to their constituencies, using these game
mechanics to make the process of coming up
with innovative ideas more game like as
opposed to just the suggestion box that
you just drop an idea in. Finally, there
are many examples of serious games in the
enterprise. So here's an example from
Siemens. The electronics and
telecommunications company where they have
created something called Plantville which
is a simulation of one of their
manufacturing plants. And they've created
a game around operating a manufacturing
plant. So this is something that can be
used for training. It's something that can
be used for other purposes to help people
understand how to be more effective in the
process of managing one of their plants.
That is I would call a, what I would call
a serious game, because it's a full-blown
game, so worth talking about within this
overall context, but worth putting, on to
the side for the moment because I want to
focus most specifically on uses of game
elements and structures that get
incorporated into existing businesses. So,
as we see a wide variety of different
kinds of applications in different kinds
of enterprises all using gamification.